<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new naked truth, or, The sandy foundation of the Sacramental test shaken, by a warning-piece discharged from heaven against all sorts of persecutors wherein you may hold Christ crucified mystically and sacramentally, upon the cross of the sacramental penal test, with all the rest of the penal laws and tests attending thereon, and contributing thereunto / by Giles Shute ...</title>
            <author>Shute, Giles, b. 1650 or 51.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 198 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3709</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11222</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11910433</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11910433</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50785</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60170)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50785)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 512:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new naked truth, or, The sandy foundation of the Sacramental test shaken, by a warning-piece discharged from heaven against all sorts of persecutors wherein you may hold Christ crucified mystically and sacramentally, upon the cross of the sacramental penal test, with all the rest of the penal laws and tests attending thereon, and contributing thereunto / by Giles Shute ...</title>
                  <author>Shute, Giles, b. 1650 or 51.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are to be sold by George Larkin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Test Act (1673)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50785:1"/>
            <p>A NEW <hi>Naked Truth,</hi> OR THE SANDY FOUNDATION OF THE Sacramental Teſt SHAKEN, BY A WARNING-PIECE Diſcharged from HEAVEN againſt all ſorts of PERSECUTORS.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN You may behold Chriſt Crucified Myſtically and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentally, upon the Croſs of the Sacramental Penal Teſt, with all the reſt of the Penal Laws and Teſts Attending thereon, and Contributing thereunto.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Giles Shute,</hi> a Friend to Chriſtian Liberty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With Allowance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be ſold by <hi>George Larkin,</hi> at the <hi>Two Swans</hi> without <hi>Biſhopſgate.</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:50785:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50785:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A New Naked Truth;</hi> Or, The <hi>Sandy Foundation</hi> of the <hi>Sacramental Teſt</hi> ſhaken, by a Warning-Piece diſcharged from Heaven againſt all ſorts of Perſecutors.</head>
            <p>GEntlemen of <hi>England,</hi> who are of Right all free born Subjects; I am ſorry that I have ſo black an Occaſion of Addreſſing my ſelf unto you in this following Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe; in which I muſt of neceſſity lay Open and Expoſe ſome very horrible ſinful Practices that has been among ſome who profeſs themſelves to be Proteſtants; namely to them which pretend themſelves to be the Moſt Infallible Sort too that are amongſt us; or elſe that Practice and Principle of theirs, in making all other peoples Spiritual Sheaves bow down unto theirs, is very unjuſtifiable, and alſo unwarrantable from the Law of God, and the Law and Light of Nature.</p>
            <p>Dear Friends, I humbly beſeech you all to read what I ſhall here offer unto you without prejudice, and conſider it without partiality, and apply it without delay; and I ſhall further more beſeech you to hear the whole concluſion of the Matter, and do not take it up and read a little, and throw it away out of your hands in Contempt and Scorn, or with Malice and Rancour of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but be adviſed by the Wiſeman, who hath ſaid, <hi>That the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of a thing is better than the beginning.</hi> And be not preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced againſt the Truth, becauſe it cometh naked unto you, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Garments of Rhetorical Expreſſions, or in the Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Humane Learning: For if you be a Lover of the Truth, you will imbrace it and find Garments for it in your own hearts, you will take it in there and cloth it, for there is the beſt clothing for Truth when all is ſaid and done that can be. O my dear
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50785:3"/>Friends, ſet open the Doors and Windows of your Souls to receive this Bleſſed Light, and do not deſpiſe your own Mercy, becauſe it cometh unto you by an Illiterate Hand, for it is ſaid in Dan. 12.3, 4. <hi>And they that be wiſe, ſhall ſhine as the Brightneſs of the Firmament; and they that turn many to Righteouſneſs, as the Stars for ever and ever: But thou, O Daniel, ſhut up the words, and ſeal the Book, even to the time of the end, many ſhall run to and fro, and knowledge ſhall be increaſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alſo I precaution others, that ſhall read this Book, that they do not make ſo unchriſtian ill uſe of it as to take up any prejudice againſt any mans perſon, who through Inadvertency are tardy of what this Diſcourſe will find out and lay open; for if you do, though I write thus againſt their Principles and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, yet I ſhall be a Witneſs againſt ye, for I write in Love to their Souls, and not in any prejudice to their Perſons; for that is no contradiction, neither is it inconſiſtent one with the other, to love a mans Perſon, and yet at the ſame time to hate his Evil Principles and Practices: It is a great Duty Incumbent upon every Chriſtian ſo to do, Matt. 5.44. <hi>But I ſay unto you, love your enemies, bleſs them that curſe you, do good to them that hate you, and pray for them which deſpightfully uſe you and perſecute you.</hi> Here you ſee is an Expreſs Command from our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and Redeemer, to love the Perſons of our Enemies, but yet we are not to love their ſinful Practiſes and Principles, for we cannot do that, but in the very Act we muſt ſin againſt God, for we are commanded to hate every abomination, and every falſe way.</p>
            <p>We are to hate what is evil in our own ſelves, yet it would be a ſin for us to hate our own Perſons. If I had an own Father that was a Drunkard or Whoremonger, I ought not to love his Drunkenneſs and Whoredom, yet I muſt not hate my Fathers Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, though I hate his Practice: therefore I do not write this to incenſe people againſt any mans perſon, though I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs this has been a Reigning Sin among the Perſecuters. And indeed there is a proneneſs in the beſt of men to this ſin: Chriſt's own Diſciples themſelves were not clear of this ſin, when they would have prayed for fire to come down from Heaven to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the very perſons of thoſe churliſh <hi>Samaritans</hi> that refuſed to give entertainment to our Saviour Chriſt; they were for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying their Perſons, and therefore Chriſt rebuked them, ſaying, <hi>Ye know not what ſpirit ye are of.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50785:3"/>
            <p>I bleſs God I have a higher and nobler End and Deſign in what I ſhall here write, than to draw out prejudice againſt any mans perſon; however I may be cenſur'd for it, I can appeal to God in ſincerity and uprightneſs of Heart in this matter, for I would not that any man ſhould be wronged of a Hair of his Head by what I ſhall here Declare to the World; but to awaken all to Repentance, <hi>For the Lion hath roared, who will not fear? The Lord God hath ſpoken, who can but propheſie?</hi> Amos 3. I am not for Diminiſhing any Gentlemans Title of Honour or Dignity, where it is properly due; <hi>Fear to whom Fear is due, and Honour to whom Honour is due</hi> — Though I muſt confeſs my Ignorance in this Matter, at the ſame time I cannot underſtand the meaning of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Lords, becauſe I can find no Scripture Authority for it at all, but rather againſt it, Matt. 20.25, 26, 27. <hi>But Jeſus called them unto him, and ſaid, Ye know that the Princes of the</hi> Gentiles <hi>exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe Dominion over them, and they that are Great exerciſe Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon them; but it ſhall not be ſo among you; but whoſoever will be Great among you, let him be your Miniſter; and whoſoever will be Chief among you, let him be your Servant.</hi> 1 Pet. 5.2, 3. <hi>Feed the Flock of God which is among you, taking the overſight thereof, not by conſtraint, but willingly; not for filthy Lucre, but of a ready Mind: neither as being Lords over Gods Heritage, but being exſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to the Flock.</hi> Our Saviour Chriſt does ſingnifie unto us that this Lording Spirit did proceed from the Heathen Idolatrous Gentiles, and that it was a uſage among them, and therefore in my Opinion it is pity that any Chriſtian Miniſters or Paſtors ſhould take it up, and exerciſe it among them. And the truth on it is — It is a very dubious point with me to determine or conclude, whether the true Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt can be Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Lords, or whether theſe Spiritual Lords can be true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Jeſus Chriſt; becauſe I cannot find that it was ſo from the beginning of Chriſt's Goſpel-Church. But this by the by. But I am clearly <hi>for rendring unto Caeſar the things that be Caeſars,</hi> and alſo to <hi>render unto God, the things that are Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My dearly beloved Countrymen, for ſo I will make bold to call you, becauſe I am an <hi>Engliſhman man</hi> born, and therefore a Member of the Body Politick of the Nation — Foraſmuch as there is a great deal of ſtickling, and ſtrugling, and ſending, and proving, <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> about theſe <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts;</hi> and much has been ſaid for the continuance of them, and much more
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50785:4"/>has been ſaid for the Aboliſhing of them; inſomuch that it is not only become a Table-talk, but it is almoſt a National Text for all People to Comment and Preach upon; therefore I ſhall ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle out one of theſe <hi>Teſts</hi> to ſpeak ſomewhat unto. And that ſhall be the <hi>Sacramental Teſt;</hi> and let us bring that to the Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of Gods Word, and let us take notice for what end that Ordinance of God was Inſtituted and Appointed, and let us hear what God the Lord will ſpeak unto us concerning this <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Teſt; And let God be true, and every man a lyer,</hi> Rom. 3.4. <hi>Should not a people ſeek unto their God? To the Law, and to the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them,</hi> Iſa. 8.</p>
            <p>Now Gentlemen, you ſhall have a Fair and Impartial Trial of this <hi>Teſt</hi> by the Word of God, and by one of your own Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Church of <hi>E.</hi> and there ſhall be none but clear and undeniable True Witneſſes, and not one Knight of the Poſt, that ſwears for Bread, among them all; although their Late Fire of Perſecution have bred whole ſwarms of thoſe ſort of Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Salamanders: And the God, who is Judge of all the Earth, ſhall be the Judge between us; which thoſe that are Perſecuters do own in Words, though in Works they deny him, Titus 1.16. <hi>They profeſs they know God, but in works they deny him, being Abominable and Diſobedient, and unto every good work reprobate.</hi> A Perſecuter, while ſuch, muſt be ſuch a perſon, or elſe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a Judge and Lawgiver unto other Mens Conſciences. Now, I ſay, I will ſingle out one of theſe <hi>Teſts</hi> to ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what unto, namely, the <hi>Sacramental Teſt,</hi> that is ſo Univerſal a <hi>Teſt</hi> amongſt them: And let us try what that will afford us, that ſo we may meaſure <hi>Hercules</hi> by his Foot. Now this <hi>Teſt</hi> was chiefly made and intended againſt all the Proteſtant Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p>And for the better coming at the making an Upright and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Judgment of this <hi>Teſt,</hi> I ſhall do three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt thing ſhall be this, I will lay down the Words of Inſtitution of this holy and bleſſed Ordinance, by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And ſecondly, I ſhall lay down the words of the Apoſte <hi>Paul</hi> to the Church of <hi>Corinth;</hi> and let us ſee what Light and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this will afford us in this matter, which is that which the Teſt-Makers, and the Teſt-Givers, and the Teſt-Takers themſelves,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50785:4"/>do all profeſs to own and practice, as well Eccleſiaſtical as Civil, as well in their Church-Government, as in the Civil State.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And thirdly and laſtly, I ſhall preſs into this ſervice one of their own 39 Articles, wherein they give the Definition of what a true Church is; and then let us try this Sacramental Teſt by theſe Infallible Rules.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt by the words of Inſtitution, by our Saviour Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as it is laid down by three of the Evangeliſts, <hi>Matt.</hi> 26.26, 27, 28. <hi>And as they were eating, Jeſus took Bread and bleſſed it, and brake it, and gave it to the Diſciples, and ſaid, Take, eat, this is my Body; And he took the Cup and gave thanks, and gave it to them; ſaying, Drink ye all of it, for this is my Blood of the New Teſtament, which is ſhed for many for the Remiſſion of Sins</hi>—Mark 14.22, 23, 24. <hi>And as they did eat, Jeſus took bread, and bleſſed, and brake it, and gave to them, and ſaid, Take, eat; this is my Body. And he took the Cup, and when he had given thanks, he gave it to them; and they all drank of it. And he ſaid unto them, This is my Blood of the New Teſtament, which is ſhed for many.</hi> Luke 22.19, 20. <hi>And he took Bread, and gave thanks, and brake it, and gave unto them, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, This is my body, which is given for you, this do in remembrance of me. Likewiſe alſo the Cup after ſupper, ſaying, This Cup is the New Teſtament in my blood, which is ſhed for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you hear what our bleſſed Saviour ſaith, by theſe three Witneſſes in the words of Inſtitution; He did not ſay, Do this to ſecure your ſelves in the Civil Government, while you do Rob and Rape, and Plunder, and Impriſon, and Spoil your honeſt peaceable Neighbours— But, <hi>Do this in remembrance of me;</hi> Here is not one word of making it a Civil Teſt, to Inſnare honeſt Men withall.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But ſecondly, Now we have heard the words of our bleſſed Redeemer; Let us alſo hear the words of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> with a reſpect to the words of Inſtitution of this bleſſed Ordinance of the Lord's Supper; And alſo the threatnings that are Annexed thereunto, againſt all Hypocritical unworthy Receivers, that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſane this Ordinance of the Lord's Supper, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30. <hi>For I have received of the Lord that which alſo I delivered unto you</hi>— (Hence you may obſerve by the way, that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, or other Miniſters of the Goſpel, ought to deliver nothing to the People, but what they firſt Receive from the Lord, and have his Word and Authority for ſo doing.) <hi>That the Lord Jeſus
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50785:5"/>the ſame night in which he was betrayed, took bread, and when he had given thanks, he brake it, and ſaid, Take, eat, this is my Body, which was broken for you, this do in remembrance of me.</hi> It was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for you Believers, and for none elſe, but ſuch as do believe, and that ſhall believe, as if the Apoſtle ſhould have ſaid. And for what end and purpoſe? why, to remember Chriſt's dear love and compaſſion, in Dying for poor ſinners, and to feed and nouriſh the new Creature, and to ſtir up and excite all the Graces of the Spirit that is in the Believer, unto a holy Commemoration of the bleſſed Effects of his Death to the Believer; and alſo to comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate the tranſcendent Love and wonderful Wiſdom and Grace and Goodneſs of God, and the great condeſcention of God, in which all his glorious Attributes were ingaged, in the contriving &amp; bringing to paſs this unparallel'd Merciful Piece of work, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Man's Redemption. But pray note by the way, that this is not a converting Ordinance, as ſome by miſtake would have it to be, becauſe no Man muſt partake of it before he is conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, becauſe that then inſtead of being converted by it, <hi>he eateth and drinketh unworthily, and ſo eateth and drinketh damnation to himſelf, not diſcerning the Lord's body.</hi> And therefore it is that we are commanded to Examine our ſelves before we partake of it, to ſee whether we be born of God, and ſo are in a converted Spiritual ſtate of Grace; and alſo to try our ſelves, whether we be in a Spiritual frame of heart, that we may know whether Grace be in Act and Exerciſe in us or not—But to Return to the words of Inſtitution—After the ſame manner alſo he took the Cup, when he had ſupped, ſaying, <hi>This Cup is the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in my Blood, this do ye, as oft as ye drink it, in Remembrance of me; for as often as ye eat this Bread and Drink this Cup, ye do ſhew the Lord's Death till he come.</hi> Here is not one word of making this Sacred Ordinance a <hi>Test</hi> to accommodate the Civil State withall, but on the contrary; as you ſhall hear by and by.</p>
            <p>For the Apoſtle bringeth it in Argumentatively, with a <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore — Whoſoever ſhall eat this Bread, and drink this Cup of the Lord unworthily, ſhall be guilty of the Body and Blood of the Lord</hi>—That is, inſtead of commemorating Chriſt's Death and Sufferings, and all the Benefits that floweth unto us from that Fountain of his precious Blood—They do eat and drink their own Damnation, without unfeigned Repentance, and God's Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Mercy; for they do crucifie to themſelves the Son of God
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50785:5"/>afreſh, and put him to an open ſhame; whoſoever ſhall eat thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, whether Lord or Commoner, let them look to it, for God is no reſpecter of Perſons, for he that feareth God, and worketh Righteouſneſs, and none but ſuch, are, or ſhall be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with him; O that all they that are thus Guilty, may tremble to think what is a coming upon them for this great Abomination of profaning the Lord's holy Supper by a Law, which I had almoſt ſaid is a National ſin, becauſe the major part of the Governing Party have been thus Guilty— Though I do hope and alſo believe, That there was many in both Houſes of Parliament, both of Lords and Commoners, when this Snare was made, that had neither heart nor hand in it; But yet notwithſtanding the major part of them muſt be for it, or it could not have been made, therefore I would not be found to grieve any of the Generation of the Righteous, without a cauſe, by condemning the Innocent with the guilty. But as the Apoſtle ſaith, Let every Man examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf whether he be guilty or not—<hi>But let a man examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſo let him eat of that Bread and drink of that Cup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here the holy Apoſtle is bringing it in again argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, by way of precaution, for ſaid he—<hi>He that eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth &amp; drinketh damnation</hi> (or condemnation) <hi>to himſelf, not diſcerning the Lord's Body; for this cauſe many are weak and ſickly among you, and many ſleep,</hi> that is, <hi>die</hi>—For what cauſe was it? why, for profaning the Ordinance of the Lord's Supper—And who was it the holy Apoſtle charged this Guilt upon? why, even upon ſome of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that believed in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for he ſaid <hi>ſome among you</hi>—They were converted, as to their Spiritual ſtate, they were in a ſtate of Grace— But yet notwithſtanding that, they were in a very carnal, looſe frame of heart: They did eat and drink worthily, as to their Spiritual ſtate; but yet nevertheleſs they did eat and drink unworthily, as to their frame of heart; and therefore God puniſhed them with corporal ſickneſſes and death, though they were free from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Death and Condemnation, by vertue of their Union with Chriſt, and ſo in a ſtate of Grace, which can never be broken, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. <hi>There is therefore now no condemnation to them that are in Christ Jeſus;</hi> that reſpects the Spiritual ſtate of the Believer— <hi>who walk not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit;</hi> The former that reſpects the State, and this later reſpects the frame of heart; in the former they are alive to God, and in the later they walk with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50785:6"/>God; The holy Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> was in a very carnal frame of heart, when he would have diſſwaded our bleſſed Saviour from ſuffering, Matt. 16.22, 23. <hi>Then Peter took him, and began to rebuke him, ſaying, Be it far from thee, Lord: this ſhall not come unto thee.— But ne turned, and ſaid unto Peter, Get thee behind me, Satan, thou art an offence unto me: for thou ſavoureſt not the things that be of God, but thoſe that be of men.</hi> That is, he was in a carnal frame of heart, in a ſudden paſſion of miſguided Love and Zeal; he was carnally minded, and our Saviour Chriſt ſaid unto <hi>Peter,</hi> in another place of Scripture, When thou art converted, ſtreng then thy Brethren; this could not be meant of his firſt converſion into a ſtate of Grace; for ſo he was converted long before that time. But it is meant of his after-converſion, unto a more Spiritual frame of heart, which he ſhould be in, after he had denied <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, Are ye not carnal, and walk as men; when one ſaith, I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> and another of <hi>Apollos,</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Cephas?</hi> That is, walk as men walketh in a carnal unregenerate ſtate; not that they were ſo, but they were even like ſuch. And the two Diſciples were in a very carnal unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving frame of heart, even on that very Day that our Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er roſe from the Dead, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.21, 25, 26. <hi>But we trusted that it had been he, which ſhould have redeemed Iſrael: and beſide all this, to day is the third day ſince theſe things were done.</hi> They looked upon themſelves to be deceived, in effect, but mind what our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſaid unto them, and alſo to us in them; Then <hi>he ſaid unto them, O fools, and ſlow of heart to believe all that the Prophets have ſpoken: Ought not Chriſt to have ſuffered theſe things, and to enter into his glory?</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, Did not all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets propheſie of my coming in the fleſh, and dying in the fleſh, and riſing again in the fleſh, and did you not ſee it with your own eyes, or might have done it, and did not I tell ye ſo my ſelf, that am the great Prophet, the head of all the Prophets, and will you not believe me, nor my Prophets, nor your own eyes neither? as if Chriſt ſhould have ſaid. This was a very carnal frame of heart indeed; and it is ſaid, <hi>To be carnally minded is death, but to be ſpiritually minded is Life and Peace;</hi> Now there is a great deal of difference between being carnally minded, and a carnal mind; as much as there is between Light and Darkneſs, or as there is between hardneſs of heart, and a hard heart; for the carnal minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the believer brings a death upon all his Graces and ſpiritual
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50785:6"/>Comforts; he is as if he was in a carnal State, with a reſpect to the comforting Evidence of it, that all lieth dead, and all the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Spirit lieth covered over with theſe Aſhes of Carnality; and that fills the Soul of the Believer full of Doubts and Fears, with a reſpect to their ſpiritual State; and puts them upon queſtioning all the Work of God upon their Soul. This carnally-mindedneſs reſpects a Child of God in a ſpiritual State, but in a carnal frame of Heart; and a carnal Mind, reſpects a carnal dead Sinner, in a ſtate of Sin and Miſery; for it is ſaid, <hi>The carnal Mind is Enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt God;</hi> for it is not ſubject to the Will of God, neither indeed can be.</p>
            <p>There may be, and too often there is, an eating and drinking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily at the Lord's Table, and that by two ſorts of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> There is many times an eating and drinking unworthily at the Lord's Table by Believers themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is always an eating and drinking unworthily at the Lord's Table, by carnal prophane Hypocrites, as often as they do partake of that Ordinance, whether Eccleſiaſtical or Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; for ſo we muſt diſtinguiſh now it ſeems; for they have made it to have a double end, Spiritual and Carnal. There muſt ever be two things to make a Man a meet or worthy Partaker of this holy Ordinance; becauſe it is a Spiritual Feaſt as much now, as it was under the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Law; for they ate and drank Chriſt under the Law, as well as we do now under the Goſpel, if you will believe the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Moreover, Brethren, I would not that ye ſhould be ignorant, how that all our Fathers were under the Cloud, and all paſſed through the Sea, and were all Baptized unto</hi> Moſes <hi>in the Cloud, and in the Sea; and did all eat the ſame ſpiritual Meat, and did all drink the ſame ſpiritual Drink; for they drank of that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Rock that followed them, and that Rock was Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.</p>
            <p>Firſt, There muſt be a ſpiritual State; all the Subjects of this Ordinance muſt be born again; they muſt be born of Water, and of the Spirit, or elſe they cannot enter into the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven here below, which is the Church-Militant; and if they be not ſo born, they cannot enter into the Kingdom of Heaven above, namely, the Church-Triumphant in Glory, <hi>John</hi> 3. for until then, they be ſpiritually dead: And what ſhall a dead, ſtinking, rotten-hearted Hypocrite do at the King of Kings Table? For Gods Eye
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50785:7"/>is upon all his Gueſt, his Eye is upon their very Heart; for God ſees not as Man ſeeth, he can ſpy out any one Soul that comes to his Table without the Wedding-Garment; God ſees what every ones end and aim is, in partaking of that Ordinance: He ſeeth them that come to eat and drink themſelves into the Government, or into a good fat place of Profit and Truſt; and ſees them that come to eat and drink at that Ordinance, to ſell <hi>Ale</hi> by vertue of it, or to bear Arms in the Train'd-Bands: And God ſaw them that were more guilty than they, namely, thoſe that gave it unto them; for all men by Nature are dead in Sins and Treſpaſſes, and all Children of Wrath, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. And therefore it may be ſaid of every carnal Sinner, as it is ſaid of the carnal lewd Woman, in the 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.6. <hi>But ſhe that liveth in pleaſure, is dead while ſhe liveth.</hi> Now ſuch as theſe be, can have no Right nor Worthineſs at all in them to partake of the Lord's Supper, no nor to adminiſter it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them neither; for they are none of Chriſt's Shepherds that doth thus, <hi>John</hi> 10.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.14. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 9.16. Now all ſuch as do exhibit this bleſſed Ordinance, and thoſe to whom it is exhibited, that are not born of God, can be but a Congregation of Hypocrites at the beſt, <hi>Job</hi> 15.34, 35. and are as loathſome as a dead ſtinking Corps would be to be placed at a Kings Table, when he made a Royal Banquet for all his Nobles; and far more loathſome too: And therefore all ſuch as theſe, <hi>eateth and drinketh Damnation to themſelves, not diſcerning the Lord's Body.</hi> And pray what can a dead Man di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern? And therefore all theſe do but make a Chain of that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance for Satan to bind them faſter to himſelf, under the guilt of all their Sins, inſtead of receiving any good or benefit by it; whereas a Child of God that cometh in a right manner, and to a right end, goeth away from that Ordinance with all his Sins par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned afreſh, and his Covenant renewed with the Lord, and rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and ſealed in the Blood of Chriſt; the others they go away with all the guilt of their Sins faſter bound, and his Covenant with Death, and his Agreement with Hell, renewed and ratified afreſh, and ſealed, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 28.15. And is not this a dreadful thing, think ye? The Lord awaken all that are thus guilty, to unfeigned Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, There muſt not only be a ſpiritual State, but there muſt be a ſpiritual frame of Heart alſo; and this latter can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be obtained before nor without the former: There muſt be a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50785:7"/>ſpiritual State, before ever there can be a ſpiritual frame of Heart; therefore every one that does not come to the Table of the Lord thus ſpiritually qualified, do come and eat and drink to themſelves Damnation, or Condemnation; aye, though he be a Child of God, and in a ſpiritual State: Nevertheleſs it is true, he doth not eat and drink eternal Condemnation to himſelf, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is in Chriſt; yet he may eat and drink the Merit of it vertually; he may eat and drink temporal Condemnation to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which may bring great temporal Judgments and Puniſhments upon him or them that thus do, even corporal Sickneſſes and Death: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89 30, 31, 32, 33, 34. <hi>If his Children,</hi> that is, Chriſt's Children, <hi>forſake my Law, and walk not in my Judgments; if they break my Statutes, and keep not my Commandments; then will I viſit their Tranſgreſſions with the Rod; and their Iniquity with Stripes: Nevertheleſs, my loving kindneſs will I not utterly take from them, nor ſuffer my Faithfulneſs to fail: My Covenant will I not break, nor alter the thing that is gone out of my Lips.</hi> God my pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh unworthy Receivers now, though in a ſpiritual State, as he did thoſe unworthy <hi>Corinthians</hi> heretofore, with Sickneſs and Death, for their prophanation of the Lord's Supper, when he may ſpare his Enemies in this Life, to puniſh them in the World to come.</p>
            <p>Thus I have ſhewed you briefly in part, what the bleſſed End and Deſign of this holy Ordinance is, and alſo the Nature and Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of it; and you may obſerve, that it is one of the great <hi>Teſts</hi> that belongeth to the truly conſtituted Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, which was made and provided in the Great Charter of Heaven, and lodged in the Church for all them, and them only, that belong to the ſpiritual Government of Heaven, namely, the true Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſts myſtical Body the Church, whereof he is the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Head and Governour, namely, the Univerſal Catholick Church: And I have in the ſecond place ſhewed what the Subjects of this Ordinance or ſpiritual Government muſt be, and how they muſt be qualified. And thirdly and laſtly, I have ſhewed ye the danger that all thoſe are in, that ruſh upon this Ordinance, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being dutly qualified and prepared for it; both of Believers in a carnal frame of Heart, and Hypocrites that are in a carnal dead ſtate of Nature.</p>
            <p>But it may be queried, Whether this ſacred Ordinance of the Lord's Supper, may not be made a Civil <hi>Teſt</hi> alſo, to accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50785:8"/>Civil Government for the Admittance of Members thereunto, and for their Confirmation therein; and for a Licenſe to ſell Ale by, and other ſecular things in this nature, as well as to be a <hi>Teſt</hi> for all them that belong to this ſpiritual Government? Unto this I will anſwer in the Negative, That it is not; for not one Soul that ever did, or that ever ſhall Receive this Holy and Bleſſed Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, out of ſuch a baſe, ſecular, prophane end and deſign, to qualifie them to come into the Government, or to ſell Ale, or any ſuch thing, but what does highly provoke God, in prophaning that ſacred Ordinance, <hi>not diſcerning the Lord's Body:</hi> And ſo they make themſelves guilty of the Body and Blood of the Lord; which is to Crucifie to themſelves the Son of God afreſh, and put him to an open ſhame. They do eat and drink themſelves into the very ſame Spirit with the unbelieving Jews, which they had in them, when they did literally, and actually, and maliciouſly Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt: So that according to this <hi>Teſteering</hi> Law, there muſt not one Soul come into the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but what muſt firſt go and Crucifie to himſelf the Son of God afreſh, and put him to an open ſhame.</p>
            <p>God hath commanded People to Crucifie their Luſts, before they can be meet or worthy to come into this ſpiritual Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and partake of the Lord's Supper, and all other Church-Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges thereunto belonging.</p>
            <p>But theſe <hi>Penal Laws</hi> or <hi>Teſt,</hi> commands Men to go and Crucifie their Lord and Maſter, before ever they can be permitted to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the Civil Government, or any of the Priviledges thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to belonging. And is not this a dreadful Law, think ye, and ſuch a myſtery of Iniquity, as is not to be parallel'd in all its Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances?</p>
            <p>Would it not be a dreadful thing, think ye, if there was a Law made, That no Man ſhould come into the Government, unleſs he would eat ſo much Rats-bane, as would fetch off all his hair off of his head and face, and fetch off all the nails from off of his fingers and toes, and lay him under a declining, waſting, lingring Diſtemper, ſo that his Life would be but a burden unto him? Why, I will be bold to ſay, That infinitely worſe is this Law of encouraging Perſons to eat and drink Damnation to themſelves, to qualifie them to come into the Government: For as the bleſſed Ordinance of the Lord's Supper is ſpiritual Food, and alſo whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Phyſick for the worthy Receivers; for in the former it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50785:8"/>feeds and ſtrengthens the new Man, <hi>viz.</hi> all the Graces of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that is in him; and by the latter all his Sins are ſubdued and mortified, and his Soul purged, and ſo kept in ſpiritual health: And thus it becomes both Food and Phyſick to the true Believers; this is a branch of the Tree of Life, the Leaves whereof are for the healing of the Nations.</p>
            <p>And ſo on the other hand, it becomes ſtrong Poyſon to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Vermine, namely, Hypocrites: It is the worſt Poyſon that ever can be thought on to them. As it is the greateſt Mercy, on the one hand, unto them that Receive it worthily, becauſe then they are as ſure to go to Heaven, as if they were there already, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they do know it or not know it themſelves; ſo on the other hand it is the greateſt Judgment under Heaven, for a Perſon to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it unworthily, in a carnal unconverted ſtate, becauſe he eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and drinketh Damnation to himſelf, <hi>not diſcerning the Lord's Body.</hi> This that is the greateſt Mercy to a Child of God, is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the greateſt Judgment to a carnal Hypocrite, that dare be ſo bold as to partake of this bleſſed Ordinance, out of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end and deſign, than what the Holy God in his Infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom has appointed it unto.</p>
            <p>O dear Souls! Do you that have been <hi>Teſt</hi>-Makers, and <hi>Teſt</hi>-Takers, and <hi>Teſt</hi>-Givers, in this ſinful way and manner, tremble to think what will become of your precious Souls, unleſs you do ſpeedily vomit up again this deadly Poyſon by unfeigned Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and thorow Reformation. God hath ſaid by his Servant St. <hi>Paul, Let a Man examine himſelf, and ſo let him eat of that Bread, and drink of that Cup:</hi> That is, he muſt try himſelf whether God by his Holy Spirit hath made him meet and worthy to partake of this holy Ordinance; that he may know in himſelf whether he be one of the Gueſt that is invited unto this bleſſed Feaſt; where they are not only to feaſt with the Lord, but upon the Lord by Faith, <hi>John</hi> 6.47, 48, 50, 63. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1, 2, 3, 4. And thereby are made worthy to take this ſpiritual <hi>Teſt</hi> of the Lord's own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, in his own way and manner, and ſo to come into the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual heavenly Government, and be made Members thereof: For <hi>whoſoever eateth and drinketh this Cup of the Lord unworthily, eateth and drinketh Damnation to himſelf, not diſcerning the Lord's Body.</hi> Here it is ſaid, <hi>Whoſoever;</hi> that is, High or Low, Rich or Poor, Prieſt or People, Lord or Commoner; this is the unalterable Law and <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of Heaven. God is no Reſpecter of Perſons,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50785:9"/>therefore look to it, you that are great Ones. And Death is no Reſpecter of Perſons alſo; for when he cometh with his Sythe, he outs down a Lord as ſoon as a Beggar,</p>
            <p>Well, thus you do hear what the Law of Heaven ſaith unto all theſe things; and now let us hear what the Laws of Men ſaith unto it alſo: Why the Laws of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> ſaith quite another thing; for they ſay tacitly and conſequentially, Let them be examined whether they have eat and drank their own Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Crucified unto themſelves the Son of God afreſh, and put him to an open ſhame; and ſo let them come into the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both of Church and State: For whoſoever, whether he be a Lord or Commoner, that ſhall come into the Government with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being thus ſinfully qualified, does incur to himſelf and Family, the Danger or Condemnation of 500 <hi>l.</hi> damage, not diſcerning or taking notice, that the Law of the Church of <hi>E</hi>— is againſt him; and that they ſhall pay it every groat on't, when ſhe hath the Whip in her hand again, and the Nation under her feet.</p>
            <p>Hence we may obſerve, That if any Perſons will come into the Government duly qualified, according to the Law in that caſe made and provided, they muſt enter in at Hells Gate; they muſt pawn, or even depoſit their very Souls, that precious Jewel that is more worth than ten thouſand Worlds, in the hands of the Devil, by eating and drinking Damnation to themſelves— And if our Saviour Chriſt does not Redeem it out of his hands again, by Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning-Mercy in his precious Blood, they will be undone and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for ever: And this is in effect to have the Government of the Nation lodged in the hands of the Devil; for according to this Law, none muſt come into it, but what muſt firſt reſign up the Conduct of their Souls unto Satan, and ſo become his Subjects, or rather his Bond-ſlaves indeed.</p>
            <p>So that inſtead of coming into the Government in Gods way, and to act for his Honour and Glory, and for the good of the whole Nation, to puniſh Sin and Iniquity, and to encourage Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; It has been made ſubſervient to promote the Devils King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Dominion, for him to Ride and Rule over Mens Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and ſo to increaſe his Subjects, and to enlarge the Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of the Prince of Darkneſs, even in the Hearts of wicked Men: For as our Saviour Chriſt has a Kingdom in the Hearts of his Saints and Servants; and as a good Governour promotes and encourages that; why even ſo on the other hand the Kingdom of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50785:9"/>Satan is encouraged by an evil Government. And is not this a dreadful Judgment for any People or Nation to lie under? And are not theſe rotten Props, think ye, to ſupport and uphold a Church or People withal? And is not this a ſandy Foundation, on which theſe fooliſh Builders do Build this Houſe of theirs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.26, 27. But it may be ſome will ſay, I am of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and it has been always my Principle thus to do, and therefore this does not concern me; but this concerns them that are of another Principle, that do take it only to come into the Government to ſave their Bacon. I confeſs this is a very ſad deplorable thing, for any that are Members of private ſeparate Congregations, that are guilty of ſuch Hypocriſie; I do not at all juſtifie them, neither does their playing the Hypocrite juſtifie you; it may harden you, but it can never juſtifie you, no more than an erroneous Principle will; for Sin is nevertheleſs an Evil, becauſe that your corrupt Principle does ſide with it. But you think you can ſin <hi>Cum priviligo;</hi> and it may be you will ſay, That you never Received the Sacrament expreſly upon this account, but as you do uſe to do at other cuſtomary times of the Year or Month: But I pray you give me leave to query with you a little upon this point: Did you never take a Certificate for ſo doing, to ſatisfie any that had power to ſcruple your coming into the Government, or into Places of Profit and Truſt, that you were thus legally qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified? Yes, that I muſt confeſs I have done: Why then that is enough; for by that you do ſignifie that you did approve of the Project, or elſe you did do a thing againſt your own Conſcience; and ſo you make your ſelf guilty either way with the reſt; and if you do approve of it, whether you had a Certificate or not, yet notwithſtanding you are guilty by Approbation in ſiding with them, from Chriſt's own Words, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.23. <hi>He that is not with me, is againſt me: and he that gathereth not with me, ſcattereth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad;</hi> as he that is not againſt Chriſt is for him, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.50. There muſt be no neutrality in this caſe; for Chriſt hates a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided Heart, <hi>viz.</hi> a Trimmer, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>I know thy Works, that thou art neither cold nor hot; I would thou wert cold or hot: So then becauſe thou art lukewarm, and neither cold nor hot, I will ſpite thee out of my mouth.</hi> As a broken Heart and a contrite Spirit is the Sacrifice that God is well pleaſed with; why even ſo on the contrary, a divided hypocritical Heart, which is that which the Sacrifice of the Wicked is always made up of, is that which is an
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50785:10"/>Abomination unto the Lord, for God hates and abhors a divided heart; But you do ſay you are of the Church of <hi>E.</hi> and it has been always your Opinion: Therefore now in the third and laſt place, I will try you by one of your own 39. Articles, namely the <hi>19th.</hi> Article, wherein it gives the Definition of a true Church, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">"The viſible Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is a Congregation of faithful Men, in the which the pure Word of God is preached, and the Sacraments be duly Miniſtred, according to <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Ordinance in all thoſe things,</q> that of neceſſity are Requiſite to the ſame; Now bring this pretended Opinion of yours to the Tryal, by your own Article, and all the reſt of your Hypocritical practices of this nature, and I am ſure this Article condemns them all, and like <hi>Goliah</hi>'s Sword, it cuts off the Neck of them all, namely of your Plundering, and Bribing, and Impriſoning, and forcing Mens Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, which practice of yours does better ſuit and agree with the Congregation of Hypocrites, in the 15 <hi>Job,</hi> 34, 35. than with the Congregation of faithful Men in the aforeſaid Article.</p>
            <p>Now ſhall any Perſons even dare to make ſo bold with the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, as to plead for the continuance of ſuch Gates of Hell, as theſe are, that have been ſo long endeavouring to prevail againſt <hi>Christ</hi>'s Church, though bleſſed be God, that That is founded upon a Rock, and his Promiſe is that they ſhall not prevail againſt it; And ſhall any chuſe rather that we ſhould continue faſt Bound ſtill under theſe Chains of Darkneſs, then to part with that Teſt, that is againſt the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> the parting with which I cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand to be a ſin, for at the worſt that can be ſuppoſed by ſlaviſh fears and jealouſies, it is but running the hazard of ſuffering by them, which is very improbable, if not impoſſible; for his Majeſty has taken a very good courſe, to cure for ever that curſed old <hi>Cain</hi>-like ſpirit of Perſecution, for has he not given ſuch a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt it, and ſuch a rebuke unto it, as the like has never been given by any Chriſtian Prince before? Has he not moſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerouſly and freely declared unto all the World, unto God, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and Men, <hi>That Conſcience ought not to be Reſtrained in Meer Matters of Religion,</hi> and that one Man ought not to Oppreſs ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man's Conſcience, that is not of the ſame Principle with himſelf? For none but God ought to Rule there; And that we ſhould do as we would be done by. And his Majeſty hath been graciouſly pleaſed to ſay, that his Parliament, when convened, may make as firm Laws, as the Wiſdom of the Nation can think
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50785:10"/>on, for the preſent and future ſecurity and enjoyment of our Chriſtian and Civil Liberty. And he will give it Royal Sanction; What can be ſaid more? As for my own part, I am very well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, that God is in all theſe things, and that he has raiſed up his Majeſty, and Anointed him for this Great Work, as he did <hi>Cyrus</hi> of old; And that he is Acted and Guided by the Spirit of God, to proceed in this untrodden ſingular way; and by a new Rule that is given Him from Heaven, the glorious Effects of which, the Generations to come, as well as this preſent Age, will have cauſe to Bleſs and Praiſe God for; and to honour his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Memory. Who then need be afraid to truſt God, and to fall in and comply with his Majeſty, in promoting this Glorious Undertaking, to compleat the Reſtoring the Empire of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and to Retrieve this poor diſtreſſed Nation, that has Lain ſo long Bleeding under theſe intolerable Yokes and grievous Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of Oppreſſion: Namely, all theſe Spiritual Penal Laws and Teſts, which ſuits better with the <hi>Turkiſh Alcaron,</hi> than with the Chriſtians Bible; or then with your own <hi>19th.</hi> Article either: The two latter of which, I do own to be good &amp; true. O my dear friends, Let us take up ſuch a reſolution, as the four Leprous Men did at the Siege of <hi>Samaria,</hi> that ſaid one to another, <hi>Why ſit we here until we Die? If we ſay we will enter into the City—then the Famine is in the City; and we ſhall Die there: and if we ſit ſtill here, we Die alſo. Now therefore, come, and let us fall to the Hoſt of the Aſſyrians, if they ſave us alive, we ſhall Live; and if they kill us, we ſhall but Die.</hi> Even ſo let us ſay of theſe Penal Laws and Teſts, if they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, and that the National Church ſhould get the whipping Power in their hands again, we are ſure to be perſecuted again, as Bad, if not worſe than ever we were yet, for they will then bring all their Eccleſiaſtical Thunder upon us again, and Deſtroy us; though bleſſed be God their Advocates does not find that the Royal Thunder is ſo eaſily brought over the head of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Gracious Declaration upon us, as they would have made the World believe it would; But if all the Penal Laws and Teſts ſhould be taken away and utterly aboliſhed, we may never ſuffer again. But however we can but ſuffer. But remember how it ſared with theſe Leprous men, they were not killed, no more do I believe that we ſhall ſuffer by it.</p>
            <p>Now in the fourth and laſt place, I ſhall make Application of this Point in two Uſes.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:50785:11"/>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> ſhall be an Uſe of Information.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Second</hi> ſhall be an Uſe of Exhortation.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>firſt</hi> place, is it ſo, as you ſee clearly proved it is, that it is ſuch an evil and dangerous thing for any Perſons to come into the Government, loaden with all theſe abominable ſinful qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, then hence we may be informed what a myſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity all thoſe Gentlemen are guilty of, that had their Heads and Hands, and Hearts ingaged in the making of this Teſt, and in Adminiſtring this Teſt, and Receiving this Teſt; Why, what were they guilty of? why, they were vertually and conſequenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally guilty of horrible Murder; what Murder? why Murder of a double and treble nature, Myſtically and Sacramentally.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They Murder the Eternal Son of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27. <hi>Wherefore, whoſoever ſhall eat this Bread, and drink this Cup of the Lord unworthily, ſhall be guilty of the Body and Blood of the Lord.</hi> All Perſons whoſoever, whether Lord or Commoner, Spiritual or Temporal, for God is no Reſpecter of Perſons—But he that feareth God, and worketh Righteouſneſs ſhall be Accepted with him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> They Murder their own Souls, <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. For <hi>he that eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh damnation to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, not diſcerning the Lord's Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>thirdly</hi> and laſtly, They do Murder their own Bodies ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citly, <hi>verſ.</hi> 30. <hi>For this cauſe many are weak and ſickly among you, and many ſleep,</hi> that is, <hi>die.</hi> And for what cauſe was it? why, <hi>for eating and drinking at the Lord's Table unworthily;</hi> as all them that take the Sacramental Civil Teſt, muſt unavoidably do, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is eſſentially ſinful, in the very End and Deſign of it, for it was never Inſtituted and Appointed for any ſuch baſe, low, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular End, by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> This informs us, that all them that are and have been Teſt-Givers, namely the Clergy, are guilty of a very hainous ſin, that have given the Sop of qualification to them that come into the Government, and to Ale-houſe-keepers, for by that they eat and drink Damnation to themſelves, and crucified to themſelves the Son of God afreſh, and put him to an open ſhame; Pray, what opener ſhame could <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Son of God be put to, then to be put to the Ale-Tub, namely to make the Sacred Ordinance of the Lord's Supper a Licenſe to ſell Ale by, which is more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker to commemorate <hi>Bacchus</hi> the God of Drunkards, than to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50785:11"/>commemorate Jeſus the God of Believers; they muſt go and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie him that ſhould be their Lord and Saviour, and eat and drink their own Damnation, before they could be duly qualified to the Juſtices humour, to ſell a Cup of Ale. Miſtake me not, I do not deſpiſe the Calling, but for the abuſe of the holy Ordinance; for the Calling is as lawful as any other Calling is, if it be not abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; for a godly Man or Woman that fells Ale, having the Grace of God in their hearts, have as good a right to that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, as any other good People have, that are of any other Calling, for indeed none but good People ought to take up that Calling, ſuch as will not ſuffer Men to drink and ſwill, until they are drunk, which is a horrible abuſe to People in this Nation, when they ſhall make no Conſcience of giving them drink, as long as they can go or ſtand, and longer too many times, but this by the by: I ſay again I do not deſpiſe the Calling, but I ſpeak againſt the abuſe of the holy Ordinance; for it would be as bad, if a Merchant were not ſuffered to trade, unleſs he did receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, becauſe the end is naught, which is confuted by the common Proverb among us, <hi>viz.</hi> the End crowns the Action, which is a great truth, for a bad end ever ſpoileth and marrs a good action, and I will not ſpeak without Book, it is a very good thing to relieve the Poor, and it is a brave thing for a Man to give his Body to be burnt for his Religion; and yet theſe two brave things may be done, and for want of a right end, they are of no value, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. <hi>And though I beſtow all my Goods to feed the poor, and though I give my Body to be burned, and have not Charity, it profiteth me nothing.</hi> You Gentlemen, that give the Sacrament to theſe baſe ſecular Ends, to qualifie Men to ſerve themſelves of the Civil State, you can be none of the Miniſters of <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> you are but Mens Miniſters at the very beſt that can be thought on. And I pray you to hear what the Apoſtle ſaith of this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked kind of medly-profanation of the Lord's Table, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.21. <hi>Ye cannot drink the Cup of the Lord, and the cup of devils; ye cannot be partakers of the Lord's Table, and of the table of devils.</hi> O Sirs! there is a dreadful Cup in the hand of the Lord, that is prepared for all you that have given the cup of Devils, or Damnation unto others, and ſo made the Table of the Lord the Table of Devils, for them to eat and drink their own Damnation upon it; What Cup you will ſay? why, look into the 75 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. <hi>For in the hand of the Lord there is a Cup, and the Wine is red and full of mixture,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50785:12"/>and he poureth out of the ſame.</hi> Thus far it was to come upon God's own People, to purge and refine them, which is, Judgment beginning at the Houſe of God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17. But the reſt of the Cup is prepared for their perſecuting Enemies; Pray Mind, <hi>But the Dregs thereof all the wicked of the Earth ſhall wring them out, and drink them:</hi> And in the 55. <hi>Iſa:</hi> 22, 23. there you have this Cup again, with the character of the Perſons that are to drink it: <hi>Thus ſaith thy Lord, the Lord and thy God, that pleadeth the cauſe of his people, Behold, I have taken out of thine hand the Cup of trembling;</hi> Out of whoſe hand? why, out of God's Peoples hand, even the <hi>Dregs of the Cup of my fury thou ſhalt no more drink it again:</hi> But our Enemies ſay we ſhall drink it again; and Unbelief and ſlaviſh fears ſaith, we ſhall drink it again; but God ſaith we ſhall not drink it again; <hi>Nahum.</hi> 1.9. <hi>What do ye imagine againſt the Lord? he will make an utter end, affliction ſhall not riſe up the ſecond time.</hi> And the Kings Majeſty ſaith, we ſhall no more drink it again, whilſt he lives—And God ſaith he will put this Cup in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hand of them that afflicted thee; which have ſaid to thy Soul, <hi>Bow Down,</hi> that <hi>we may go over;</hi> and thou haſt laid thy Body as the Ground, and as the Street to them that went over; this Bowing the Soul, was to have them proſtrate their Souls, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice their Conſciences unto their Luſts, to defile their Souls and Conſciences, by a ſinful complyance, by conforming to that Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that has none of the Sanction of God upon it, nor none of God's Authority for it, by which they would ſin againſt God, and provoke him to Anger; but they refuſed to do that, and did chuſe rather to expoſe their Body, to lay that as the Ground, and the Street to them to go over; You know the Ground is trodden under foot, and it is paſſive, and the Street is common for all Paſſengers; Why ſo our Body, which comprehends all our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Enjoyments, was laid as the Ground, and the Street, for them to go over; namely, Eſtates, Liberty, Relations, and the like, all was expoſed to the Cruelty and Malice of our Enemies; Look back, and conſider whether it has not been ſo? if you cannot tell, I can tell by woful experience; But we would not Bow our Souls, but did rather chuſe to Suffer than to Sin, which was in obedience to that command of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to deny our ſelves, and take up our Croſs, and to follow him; But when was this Cup to be put into the hand of the wicked? why, after God had done puniſhing and purging his own People for their ſins by them. It was to ſucceed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50785:12"/>this laying the People of God's Bodies as the ground, and as the ſtreet, unto them that went over: And another Character when it was to be is this, When God who is Judge of all the Earth, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth down one, and ſetteth up another, as you may ſee in the Verſe before the Cup is prepared, in that Pſalm, 75.7. O Sirs! you ought to have fed the Flock with wholeſome Goſpel-Food like good Shepherds; you ſhould have preached the pure Word of God faithfully, and miniſtred the Sacraments duely, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your Nineteen Articles, as I hope and do believe ſome did, for I will not condemn all, I hope ſome of you did ſeparate the precious from the vile, <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.19. <hi>And if thou take forth the precious from the vile, thou ſhalt be as my Mouth; let them return unto thee, but return not thou unto them.</hi> Did you do ſo, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men? Did you take forth the precious from the vile? O no! But you have given the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper to whole droves of the vileſt of Men. Gentlemen, pray be not angry with me for dealing thus plainly with you; I am ſure a good Man will not; for I cannot ſew Pillows under your Elbows; for I can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to God, That I wiſh you no hurt in the leaſt degree, neither will I give any worſe Character of you, than the holy Scriptures does infallibly give to Men that are guilty of what you are and have been guilty of: And therefore if you will be angry, you would do well to be angry with your own ſinful Practices, which have brought you and laid you under theſe black Characters; for it is only to ſuch I now ſpeak, and not to the upright in Heart. Pray hear what our Saviour ſaith unto you, and alſo of your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, in <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.7, 8, 9, 14. Though this was ſpoken unto the <hi>Jews,</hi> yet it is applicable unto you that tread in their ſteps, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.13, 14, 16. And hear what the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, Chap. 56, v. 10, 11, 12. and apply it: <hi>His Watchmen are blind, they are all ignorant; they are all dumb Dogs, they cannot bark, ſleeping, lying down, loving to ſlumber; yea, they are greedy Dogs which can never have enough, and they are ſhepherds which cannot underſtand; they all look to their own way, every one for his gain from his Quarter: Come ye, ſay they, I will fetch Wine, and we will fill our ſelves with ſtrong drink; and to morrow ſhall be as this day, and much more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, We may learn hence what a dreadful thing theſe <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts</hi> are: It is the very Ground and Foundation for Perſecution; it is that which gives Being to the Spirit of Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50785:13"/>this <hi>Salamander</hi> is bred in this ſire of Hell; it is that which gives life to the Image of the Beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.15. It corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borates and ſtrengthens the hands of Perſecuters, who are and have been in all Ages the vileſt and baſeſt of Men: <hi>Acts</hi> 7.5. <hi>But the Jews which believed not, moved with Envy, took unto them certain lewd fellows of the baſer ſort, and gathered a Company, and ſet all the City in an uproar; and aſſaulted the Houſe of</hi> Jaſon, <hi>and ſought to bring them out to the People.</hi> Why, what was the matter? why there had been a Conventicle at his Houſe; and miſſing the moſt part of the People, (<hi>v.</hi> 6, 7.) they took <hi>Jaſon</hi> the Man of the Houſe, and them which they took with him, and bound them over to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer at their Seſſions. I ſuppoſe hence we may obſerve in the firſt place by the way, That Perſecuters are the Tumult-Raiſers and common Diſturbers of Cities and Nations. Secondly, That the charging the peaceable People of God with Riots and Routs, and diſturbing the Peace, is an old trick of the Devil. And thirdly and laſtly, binding over Perſons for Worſhipping God, is a very ancient thing alſo.</p>
            <p>A Perſecutor is one that muſt abandon all moral Honeſty; he muſt do as he would not be done by; he muſt ſacrifiee his Conſcience, and pawn his Soul, in the Hands of the Devil, for he muſt perſecute Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.4, 5. and fight againſt God, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.38, 39. A Perſecuter is one that bids Defiance to Heaven, and is in open Hoſtility and Rebellion againſt the Almighty, and he is ſtriking at the Apple of God's Eye; <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.8. <hi>For thus ſaith the Lord of Hosts, after the Glory hath he ſent me unto the Nations which ſpoiſed you;</hi> (do you hear, you perſecuting Spoilers of the Nation) <hi>for he that toucheth you, toucheth the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his Eye,</hi> that is, of God's Eye.</p>
            <p>Again, A Perſecuter is worſe than the Devil in ſome Reſpects; for the Devil cannot force a man to ſin, he can but tempt and ſuggeſt to Sin; but the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor does both; he tempts them to conform to a Religion or Worſhip, that they are convinc'd in their Conſciences is not right, becauſe it has none of the Sanction of God's Authority upon it; and if they refuſe, then he does what he can to force them, by Indictments and Fines, and Excommunications, and Plundering, and Impriſoning them, and the like: Now, this the Devil cannot do himſelf perſonally, therefore they are worſe then the Devil.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Fourthly,</hi> A Perſecutor, or one that hath this <hi>Cain</hi>-like Spirit in him, every time he ſaith the <hi>Lord's Prayer,</hi> he ſpeaks Blaſphemy, for he does blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the Name of God the Father, the firſt Perſon in order in the Bleſſed and Glorious Trinity; for he begins it in Blaſphemy; for he ſaith, <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven:</hi> And the holy Word of God ſaith, That <hi>no man can call God Father, but by his Spirit; for let him that taketh the Name of the Lord in his Mouth, Depart from Iniquity;</hi> and the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Know ye not that the Spirit of Chriſt is in ye, except ye be Reprobate?</hi> And our Lord Jeſus Chriſt told the old Sect of <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> that were Perſecuters, as our New-Goſpel-Sect
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50785:13"/>of the ſame Leven are, in <hi>John</hi> 8.44. <hi>Ye are of your Father the Devil, and the Luſts of your Father ye will do: He was a Murtherer from the beginning, and abode not in the Truth.</hi> Why! So all his Children departs from the Truth; when they turn Perſecuters, they do not do as they would be done by; they depart from that Truth, which the very light of Nature doth teach us, as well as the Word of God. Now can it ever be poſſible, that a Child of the Devil can call God Father, without being guilty of Blaſphemy at the ſame time; for he ſaith, <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> when as his Father is the Devil; ſo that by his Lye, he does tacitly and conſequentially pull God out of his Throne of Mercy, and place his Father the Devil in his room, upon the Mercy Seat in Heaven, and puts up his Petition to the Devil, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Praying unto God his Maker: And is not this a dreadful Caſe?</p>
            <p>Nay further in the fifth place, for I have not done with ye yet: When a Perſecuter doth ſay the Lord's-Prayer, he doth ſay, <hi>Thy Kingdom come, thy Will be done in Earth as it is in Heaven.</hi> And no Perſons are ſo great Oppoſers of Chriſt's Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Kingdom coming, as the Perſecuters are; and none does oppoſe the doing of God's Will in Earth as it is in Heaven, like them of a perſecuting Spirit; for in Heaven there God's Will is done uninterruptedly by Angels, and all other Glorified Spirits; there they Praiſe God in perfect Peace, Love, and Union; there is no Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter there, nor none to diſturb nor make them afraid; for there they are all of one Heart, and of one Mind. But ſo it cannot be done in Earth by the Perſecuters, who cannot ſleep unleſs they do Miſchief, and they do hinder others from <hi>doing the Will of God in Earth, as it is done in Heaven;</hi> therefore a Perſecuter cannot be ſincere and in good earneſt, when he ſaith, <hi>Thy Kingdom come, thy Will be done in Earth, as it is in Heaven;</hi> Therefore all they of a perſecuting Spirit, do but diſſemble and mock God, and tell him a parcel of Lies to his very Face, for they do ſay in Words, <hi>that God's Will muſt be done in Earth, as it is in Heaven;</hi> but in Works they do utterly deny it; for they Dethrone the Almighty, <hi>who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,</hi> as much as in them lyes. And the proud Perſecuters do mount God's Throne here on Earth, namely, the Souls and Conſciences of men, and ſay to their Souls, <hi>Bow down, that we may go over:</hi> They do rob God of his Sovereignty, and become ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Legiſlators to make Laws, and give Laws unto their Fellow-creatures to Worſhip God by, as they pretend, and ſo do wreſt the Government out of God's Hand, over the Souls and Conſciences of men, which is peculiarly belonging to the Great and Dread Sovereign Majeſty of Heaven and Earth, which is to do their Father the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil's will on Earth, as it is done in Hell: And not to <hi>do God's Will in Earth, as it is in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Sixthly,</hi> A Perſecuter, as often as he ſaith the Lord's Prayer, does in Effect Pray, that God would not forgive him his Sins; for he ſaith, <hi>Forgive us our Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, as we forgive them their Treſpaſſes againſt us.</hi> Now a Perſecuter cannot ſay this heartily and ſincerely, becauſe that inſtead of praying to God, he does imprecate the foreſt of Judgments upon himſelf; for he ſaith, <hi>Forgive us our Treſpaſſes, as we forgive them their Treſpaſſes againſt us,</hi> and the Perſecuter did not, nor yet does not forgive the Diſſenters, though but pretended Treſpaſſes againſt them, when ſome Perſons have fallen into their hands by their Nonconformity in the matter of Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of God, when they have deſired them to be favourable unto them, and have told them, if they did proceed to the Rigour of their Law, they would ruine them, and their Wife and Children; they would not hearken unto them, unleſs they would bow down their Soul unto them, that they might go over, namely, to Conform, ſo that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50785:14"/>they muſt Treſpaſs againſt God, or elſe they would not forgive them their pretended Treſpaſſes againſt them, which made the Remedy infinitely worſe than the Diſeaſe; and ſo they choſe rather to lay their Bodies with the Ground, and as the Street for them to go over, then that they would ſin againſt God, by conforming, which was paſſive Obedience of the right kind; therefore the Perſecuters do Pray, that God would not forgive them their Sins; for Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>But if ye forgive not men their Treſpaſſet, neither will your Father forgive you your Treſpaſſes,</hi> Mat. 6.15.</p>
            <p>Now, if the Perſecuters did run their Hatred and Malice to the very uttermoſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Perſecuting Laws, and further too; and are now contending to keep the ſaid Laws for Perſecution ſake, in hopes to revenge themſelves upon the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> by venting their Envy and Malice againſt them, who deſires that no worſe thing may come unto them, then that they may all turn to be honeſt Men and Good Chriſtians, which while they are Perſecutors, they are neither; therefore, while the Spirit of Perſecution is in them, I would adviſe them to forbear ſaying the <hi>Lord's Prayer,</hi> which is too Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Sacred a Prayer, for ſuch profligate Wretches to take into their Mouths: But let him that taketh the name of God in his Mouth, <hi>Depart from Iniquity;</hi> for if God ſhould forgive the Perſecuters, no more than they forgive the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> then they muſt periſh and be Damned for ever. Therefore inſtead of Praying to God for pardoning Mercy, they do imprecate the worſt of Judgments to come upon them; namely, that God would not pardon them: Look to it all you Perſecuters, for the Lord is at hand, and you will be the firſt that will be called to the Bar to take your Tryal, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.27. <hi>But thoſe mine Enemies which would not that I ſhould Reign over them, bring hither, and ſlay them before me.</hi> Ay! Chriſt will ſee the Execution done upon them himſelf, for they are the greateſt Enemies that Chriſt has upon the Face of God's Earth.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Perſecuters are the very Peſt of a Nation, or Kingdom; for they ſeparate Subjects from their Prince, and from their Native Countrey; and ſo De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>populate Kingdoms, and deſtroy Trade, and impoveriſh Nations; and they do ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Parents from their Children, and Husbands from their Wives, and cauſes Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and Wars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They do ſeparate Subjects from their Prince, and Depopulate their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and Impoveriſh Nations by deſtroying Trade; for Perſecution does always drive out, and drive away many of the Inhabitants of the Land into other Countries, beſides what they ruine and deſtroy at Home in naſty Goals, and with Grief and Poverty; for when they are perſecuted at one place, they fly to another: And the <hi>Wiſeman</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.28. <hi>In the Multitude of People is the King's Honour: But in the want of People is the Deſtruction of the Prince:</hi> And by this means Trade is deſtroyed, and the Peace diſturbed, and the Treaſure of a Nation or Kingdom is Exhauſted and Dreined away, which is the very Sinews, and Veins, and Blood, ay, and the Life too, of the Body Politick of a Nation: And that Nation that giveth Liberty, is thereby Inriched; for by that means they become a Drein unto thoſe Kingdoms or Nations that do perſecute. For firſt, they drein away their People, which is the Honour, and Glory, and Strength of a King; For, what is a King or Kingdom, without People? It is like a Gentleman, without Means or Wealth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Thoſe that give Liberty of Conſcience, they drein away the Wealth and Treaſure of a Nation that does perſecute, which does mightily Inrich the former, and Impoveriſh the latter; and this is the very cauſe, that makes our Eaſtern Neighbours ſtickle ſo much as they do, againſt the Eſtabliſhing of our Chriſtian Liberty by a <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and that is the Reaſon why that Eaſt-Wind does bring over ſo many
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50785:14"/>Locuſts and Catterpillers, to eat up every green thing of this our <hi>Chriſtian Liberty.</hi> Namely, Their Pamphlets that are ſtuft with frighful Notions, to Create and Foment Fears and Jealouſies, to infuſe hard Thoughts into the Minds and Hearts of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, concerning his Majeſties Intentions and Deſigns, in giving this Liberty unto us; I do not remember that ever they were ſo kind to the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> in the late horrid Perſecution, as to interceed with the Church of <hi>England</hi> on their behalf, to abate their Rigour: O no, for that <hi>Northerly</hi> Wind blew them a great deal of Corn; for by this Craft, or rather Cruelty of the Perſecuters here, they got a great deal of Wealth there, as well as our Crafts-men that belongeth to <hi>Diana</hi> here, and that maketh them and the other ſtickle, as they do at this time againſt the Aboliſhment of the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts;</hi> but it is my Opinion, that both the one and the other might be far better Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, in humbling themſelves before the Lord for their own Sins; let them both look at home; let them pull the Beam out of their own Eye, before they go about to pull the Mote out of their Brothers, <hi>Matt.</hi> 7.5. <hi>Thou Hypocrite, firſt caſt out the Beam out of thine own Eye, and then ſhalt thou ſee clearly to caſt out the Mote out of thy Brothers Eye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay again, Let them both begin at home, for God hath a Controverſy with them both; againſt the one, for their Bloody Perſecution and prophaning the Sacred Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Lord's Supper, and their grievous Oppreſſion: And God hath a Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy againſt the other, for Prophaning the Lord's Day, and for Swearing <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento,</hi> and for their Drunkenneſs; and let them repent of it all, and of their great Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard-of <hi>Epicurian</hi> Abominable Gluttony; and let them repent of their Whoredoms and Uncleanneſs, and all other Abominations, that is to be found amongſt ſome of the Magiſtrates themſelves, which ſhould be the Reformers of a Nation; unto whoſe Care the ſanctifying and keeping holy the Sabbath is committed, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.20, 21. <hi>Neh.</hi> 17.18. I have been Credibly Informed, That the Magiſtrates themſelves do countenance and indulge men to work upon their own Ships, to fit them to Sea, on the Lord's Day, and to do any other Work, or to Feaſt and Riot on that Day, without Countroul; and will not God Viſit for theſe things, think ye? Notwithſtanding the great ſtickling of the <hi>North</hi> Country Gentlemen, that has formerly been of another Religion.</p>
            <p>Surely, if <hi>Noah, Daniel</hi> and <hi>Job</hi> could not prevail with the Lord to turn away Wrath from a People, I cannot think that he can be very acceptable with the Lord, who hath put off his Coat and graſp'd another Religion, then what he was Born and Bred to, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.4, 5. <hi>Nevertheleſs, I have ſomewhat againſt thee, becauſe thou haſt left thy firſt Love; remember therefore from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and do the firſt Works, or elſe I will come unto thee quickly, and will remove thy Candleſtick out of his place, except thou repent.</hi> And what is ſaid here of a Church, and to a Church, is applicable alſo to particular Perſons: And let him return to his <hi>firſt Love,</hi> and not ſtickle ſo much againſt our preſent Liberty, leaſt he and all that taketh that courſe, be found even to oppoſe or fight againſt God: Mind what Counſel that honeſt Man <hi>Gamaliel</hi> gave to the Old Perſecuting ſuperſtitious <hi>Jews,</hi> in almoſt a parallel caſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.38.39. And now I ſay unto you, <hi>Refrain from theſe men, and let them alone, for if this Counſel or this Work be of men, it will come to nought; but if it be of God, ye cannot overthrow it, leaſt haply ye be found, even to fight againſt God.</hi> O! that we might all repent, and return to our Allegiance to God, eſpecially ſuch as have and are yet ſtill taking wrong ſteps out of Gods way, for God is a coming to call us to account for what we have been doing, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.8. <hi>The Lyon bath Roared, who will not fear? The Lord God hath ſpoken, who can but Propheſie?</hi> And although I am not a Prophet, nor the Son of a Prophet, yet this I will boldly Aſſert, That without a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50785:15"/>Repentance; and a thorough Reformation of theſe two ſorts of People at home and abroad, that are ſo much againſt this our <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> that God hath ſent us from Heaven by the Hands of his <hi>Gracious Majeſty,</hi> God will bring ſome tremendous Judgment upon them both, for they have no other ſolid Reaſon for it at the bottom, but becauſe it does ſeem to interfere with their Worldly Secular Intereſt, as if their happineſs did lye wholly in our Miſery; they had rather that we ſhould lye under the heavy Burdens of Oppreſſion of Conſcience, then that they ſhould be prevented of making themſelves Rich and Great, by our Inevitable Ruine and Deſtruction. And is this to walk according to the <hi>Golden Rule of Christ,</hi> to do to others as we would be done by? It is true, our <hi>Eaſt</hi> Countrey Neighbours do give <hi>Liberty of Conſcience;</hi> and the thing is very well, and it is good in it ſelf; but yet I muſt tell ye, they could do no leſs in point of Prudence to themſelves, for by that Liberty and their Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Peoples Captivity, in a great meaſure, they ſtand, and grow Great and Potent, which is honeſt Policy I muſt confeſs: But I am apt to think it is not much more then Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Policy, as you ſhall hear, if you do weigh and conſider the thing well in its full Latitude, for they do owe much of their Greatneſs to the Spirit of Perſecution and Oppreſſion: But if the reſt of the Neighbouring Princes do but follow the Example of His Majeſty of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> in giving and eſtabliſhing <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> in meer Matters of Religion, upon laſting Foundations, which I hope, and am very inclinable to believe they will in a ſhort time, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.16, 16. which would make their Crowns ſit faſter and firmer upon their Heads, and the <hi>Jewels</hi> thereof to ſhine more conſpicuouſly in the Eyes of God, and in the Hearts of their beſt Subjects, which is far more pleaſing to God and all good Men, then to have it wreathed about with the Oppreſſed Conſciences of their Subjects; like unto a Crown of <hi>Thorns,</hi> to ſcratch the Souls of their People; why then our <hi>Eaſt</hi> Country Neighbours might reſt ſatified, and ſit down in Peace under their own Vine, and under their Fig-Tree, and be contented with what they have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, for they have catcht a great deal of Fiſh in our troubled Waters, which I do not begrudge them in the leaſt: But yet notwithſtanding, I would not have them endeavour to Undermine and do what in them lyes, to overthrow our <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> by their Pamphlets; and eſpecially as they have done by that ſpecious Letter, wherein they cunningly inſinuate a pretence of being willing to afford us a <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> which is but juſt next door to a greater Captivity, or a Shooing-Horn unto it, which any Man almoſt, though he had never been at the Univerſity, nor yet at the Inns of Court, might ſee through and through it, without the help of a pair of Spectacles: The worthy Getleman preſcribes a Liberty for the Exerciſe of our Religion, it is true; but if you look into the bottom of it, you will find that it is but <hi>Durante beneplacito.</hi> It ſhall be but as long as our Enemies pleaſes; for as I take it, he ſaith it is fit that all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould have the Liberty of Worſhiping God according to their ſeveral Perſwaſions, which is very good ſo far; but ſays he, It is not fit or ſafe, that the Legiſlative Power ſhould be lodged in any other Peoples Hands, but theirs of the National Church; or Words to that effect: As if the Worthy Gentleman ſhould have ſaid, That all the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> of all ſorts, are either Knaves or Fools, or Children under Age, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not worthy or fit to be truſted with their Inheritance, namely, <hi>Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> and the Security of it, but muſt be under Tutours and Governours, and chuſe themſelves Guardians: And it is not fit that they ſhould intruſt themſelves with their own ſhare of the Government, according as his Gracious Majeſty would have them, which is to have them that hate us to have the ſole Rule and Government over us, which is Ranked in the holy Scripture, among the greateſt of Judgments that God does bring upon a People or Nation.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:50785:15"/>
            <p>And who is ſo blind as they, that will not ſee into this Intrigue or Wheedle? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this great Man takes the Diſſenters to be very great Fools, or very little Children; Pray, What kind of Security can ſuch a kind of Security give us? And what can any ſuch kind of Liberty afford us Diſſenters, of all ſorts, in <hi>Terra Firma,</hi> where we are not under an abſolute neceſſity to give Liberty of Conſcience, for to get Bread for the Nation? If it were ſo, then the Parallel with their Government, would hold Water in ſome Meaſure. But as the Caſe and Circumſtance with us, is far otherwiſe then that with them, therefore the Gentleman meaſures by a wrong Rule, and is out, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as we ſay, he muſt begin again, and go upon another Topick; for this will not do with us, as not being laid under a general neceſſity of giving Liberty of Conſcience, as they are: for here, if the Church of <hi>England</hi> have the ſole Legiſlative Power in their Hands, they may give us Liberty one Seſſions of Parliament to quiet us, and to ſerve a Turn; and the next Seſſions, they may take it away again, and ruine, and undo us; and ſuch a kind of Liberty as this, would not be worth two years Purchaſe of any Man's Money in <hi>England:</hi> Pray, What is the Reaſon that the People of <hi>England,</hi> that are of the ſame Rellgion with the Church-of-<hi>England</hi>-men in <hi>London,</hi> do not ſuffer them to chooſe all their Burgeſſes, and Knights of the Shire, in <hi>London,</hi> for all the reſt of the Nation, being they are ſo near to the Parliament-Houſe, and all of one Religion, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to put the Counties and Corporations, to ſo much trouble and charge? What an unreaſonable ſtrange Queſtion is this? Why! Pray what is the Reaſon? Why, It is becauſe they will have ſome of their own Neighbours and Friends there, that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed Men in the Countrey, to Repreſent their Neighbours, and to Redreſs their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grievances, and to Defend and Secure their Priviledges, and to Prevent others for lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more Taxes upon them than their ſhare. Well, if the Church-of-<hi>England</hi>-Men will not truſt one another in leſſer matters, who are all of one Religion, how much leſs Reaſon have all ſorts of Diſſenters to truſt them? And how much more Reaſon, have all ſorts of Diſſenters, to have their Proportion of Repreſentatives in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-Houſe, to defend and ſecure them, in all their proper Rights and Priviledges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing unto them, both as Men and Chriſtians; that they might not be ruined and undone, by cruel oppreſſing Laws, and have no Party in the Houſe to oppoſe them, and to ſpeak a Word for them? How unreaſonable a thing is it, that ſuch a vaſt body of People, as the Diſſenters of all ſorts do make in <hi>England,</hi> ſhould be Excluded the Government? I will appeal to God, Angels and Men, of the Injuſtice and In-equality of the thing: And thus you do ſee the Scope and Drift of the Letter, and how this great Eaſt-Countrey-Gentleman has trick'd upon us.</p>
            <p>Therefore I am apt to think, and am jealous, that they themſelves do not give Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, for Chriſtian Liberty's-ſake; that is, they do not give it ſo much for God's ſake, as for their own. For if they give Chriſtian Liberty for God's-ſake, or for Chriſtian Liberty's-ſake; then to be ſure, they would be as willing to have it granted in other Countries as in their own; and if ſo, then they would not fill our Ears with din as they do; but they give Liberty of Conſcience out of civil Policy, and not ſo much religiouſly, or for Religion's-ſake; for the end and deſign Crowns the Action; for a Man may do a good thing, but yet it may be to a bad End, and that marrs and ſpoils all, not that civil Policy is to be condemned, if it be to a civil End. And the Truth on it is, whether this Liberty they give, may be properly called Chriſtian Liberty, or whether it may not as well be called Licentiouſneſs, is a great Queſtion with me? Or, Whether it may not fall much about equal between both? Whether there be not as much Liberty and Indulgence, given to Sin and Luſt, as there is given to a well-ordered Chriſtian Liberty of Conſcience? For I cannot tell, whether they ever told the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50785:16"/>World, that Conſcience ought not to be reſtrained in things that relate to Matters of meer Religion and Worſhip, as his Gracious Majeſty hath done. Thus you ſee in part, how Perſecuters do Depopulate Kingdoms and Nations, and Deſtroy Trade, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and Impoveriſh the People; and are the Dogs that hunts the Burroughs, and brings out the Game for others to take as well as themſelves; and are the greateſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, that Princes and their good Subjects have under the Sun. They may mock and ſcoff at poor Captives, that are willing to have their Yokes and Snares broken off, and taken away, by accepting of Chriſtian Liberty, while we are labouring in the Fire to accompliſh it, when God in his Infinite Wiſdom and Goodneſs, by the Hand of his Gracious Majeſty, does offer it unto us, to compleat it, by their Expoſing of us, by their Ridiculous <hi>Painted Chariot:</hi> But they may aſſure themſelves, that there is a fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chariot hangs over their Heads, and will certainly come down upon them, without a very ſpeedy, unfeigned Repentance, and thorow Reformation: As ſafe and ſecure as they think themſelves to be, they may ſport and play like <hi>Leviathan</hi> with Painted Chariots, and ſlight and deſpiſe the great and wonderful Providences of God; but they will have other Apprehenſions of things in a little time: Look for it, Expect it, and Prepare for it, and that quickly too.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Secondly,</hi> Perſecuters ſeparates the tender Parents from their beloved Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and the affectionate Husband, from his dearly beloved Wife: It may be the Father, or Husband is in a ſtinking naſty Priſon, and his Houſe Rifled and Plundered, and his poor Wife laid upon a fick Bed, if ſhe have one left, with Grief and Sorrow, occaſioned by theſe Cruelties; and the poor Babes crying for the abſence of their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned tender Father, and for the Affliction of their grieved Mother; and it may be, the poor Children are crying for Bread alſo; And what Heart, but that of Stone, will not relent and be grieved at this? O Sirs! I would have all you that are of a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Spirit, amongſt us here, and alſo thoſe Eaſt-Countrey-Gentlemen, that are ſtickling againſt our Chriſtian Liberty there, for they are all of a perſecuting Spirit, with theſe here, even tremble to think what will become of you; for though they brag of giving Liberty of Conſcience at home, yet they are againſt it abroad, which is an infallible Argument with me, that they do not give Liberty of Conſcience upon a right gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Chriſtian Principle: That is thus, They do not give it ſo much for God's ſake, as for their own, as I ſaid before.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and Laſtly, Perſecution is the Father of Rebellion, and the Mother of Wars, <hi>James</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. <hi>From whence comes Wars and Fighting among you? Come they not henèe, even of your Luſts, that war in your Members? Ye Luſt, and have not: Ye kill, and deſire to have, and cannot obtain: Ye Fight and War, yet ye have not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye ask amiſs, that ye may conſume it upon your Luſts.</hi> And <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>That Oppreſſion maketh the Wiſe Man mad.</hi> And no Man can be ſaid, to be truly wiſe, but him that is really good; and they are generally ſuch, as are the Subjects of this kind of Oppreſſion, which is the greateſt Oppreſſion of all; for there is nothing dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the World to a good Man, than Liberty to ſerve and worſhip God, according to his Light and Knowledge that God has given him: But here is a wiſe man, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a good Man, and yet a mad Man; And what made him ſo? Why, the Text tells us, that it is Oppreſſion: Well! And what is a mad Man? And what does a mad Man do? Why! Firſt, A mad Man is one that is beſides himſelf, he hath loſt his Reaſon, as to the Exerciſe of it, which ought to be his Rule to walk by; that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn, and he does that which he would not do, if he was himſelf. And <hi>Secondly,</hi> He grows reſolute and deſperate. And <hi>Thirdly,</hi> and <hi>Laſtly,</hi> He betaketh himſelf to undue Means for his Relief, perhaps he flies to an arm of Fleſh, for to eaſe himſelf,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50785:16"/>inſtead of flying to God, and relying upon him; and this is the Fruits and Effects of Perſecution; and therefore all the Wars and Rebellions that have been among us, ought to be charged principally to the foot of the Perſecutors Account.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly</hi> and <hi>Laſtly,</hi> A Perſecutor is one, that is an incarnate Devil; for this is that Devil, that doth caſt the Saints and Servants of God into Priſon, that we read on in <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10, <hi>Fear none of theſe things which thou ſhalt ſuffer; behold, the Devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into Priſon.</hi> Shew me a Perſon that is a Perſecuter, and at the ſame time, I will ſhew you an Incarnate Devil.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> This great Truth informs us, that all thoſe that are afraid to part with all thoſe <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> that keep men out of Government, upon account of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and that for fear of Popery, are more afraid of uncertain future ſuffering, then of continuing under certain preſent ſinning againſt God; for they do tacitly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentially, and unadviſedly chooſe, rather that Chriſt ſhould remain ſtill Crucified, by this horrible Law of the Sacramental Teſt, which obligeth a Man to Crucifie his Redeemer that ſhould be, and that before he can be duely qualified to come into the Government, then they will part with the <hi>Teſt,</hi> that is againſt the <hi>Romaniſts:</hi> Theſe be the 19th Article-men of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and ſome other good Men who are afraid to part with the <hi>Teſt</hi> upon another account, then that of the Perſecuting part of the ſaid Church are; for the Perſecuting part of it cannot think of being ſatisfied and content to enjoy what is their own proper Right and Priviledge, but are like wicked <hi>Ahab,</hi> they muſt be coveting their Brothers Vine-yard, they cannot ſubmit willingly to part with their Domineering Prelatick Lording Power over their Fellow-Subjects, they muſt be Lording it over God's Heritage, though we bring them the great <hi>Charter</hi> and <hi>Canon</hi> Law of Heaven that forbids it. Pray read this part of the <hi>Charter of Heaven,</hi> and there you may find <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> aſſerted, without any <hi>Humane Teſt</hi> to prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite it, in the 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2, 3. <hi>Feed the flock of God which is among you, taking the overſight thereof, not by conſtraint, but willingly.</hi> Do you hear, Gentlemen, what your Duty is? And alſo you may ſee what your Sin hath been, you that have not kept to your 19th Article: But ſtay, the Apoſtle hath not done with you yet, for as you muſt not be conſtrained to do your Duty, but you muſt do it willingly; ſo it muſt not be done in covetouſneſs; <hi>Not for filthy Lucre, but of a ready Mind; Neither as being Lords over Gods Heritage, but being Enſamples to the Flock.</hi> Thus you hear what St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith; but it may be, they may ſay of St. <hi>Peter as</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> did ſay of him (and St. <hi>John</hi>) <hi>That they were <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlearned and Ignorant Men, Acts</hi> 4.13. And as they do Cavel and Quarrel with all them that Write Books, or Preach the Goſpel, that do not underſtand Hebrew, Greek and Latin well; therefore let us hear what Learned St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, and hear whether he was for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> or not; and whether he was for having or appointing any <hi>Humane Teſt,</hi> to ſecure our <hi>Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> unto us; pray mind 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. <hi>Not for that we have Dominion over your Faith.</hi> Here the Apoſtle diſclaims all Lording Soveraignty over Men's Conſciences; there is your Liberty, <hi>But are helpers of your Joy;</hi> But they that are againſt <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> that Oppreſs the <hi>Conſciences,</hi> are the greateſt Enemies to Joy in the whole World, be they who they will, <hi>For by Faith we ſtand.</hi> Where was the Apoſtle when he ſaid this? Why even in the midſt of all his Enemies. Why ſurely St. <hi>Paul</hi> and our Humane Projecters were not of one and the ſame Opinion; for they ſay, That by the <hi>Teſt</hi> againſt the <hi>Romanists</hi> they ſtand: But the holy Apoſtle, when he was in Ten times more danger then we are, ſaid, <hi>By Faith we ſtand:</hi> There was his <hi>Teſt</hi> which he Relied on under God, when he had not a Prince to ſtand by him, and tell him, that <hi>Conſcience</hi> ought not to be reſtrained. And it is ſaid in the holy Scripture, <hi>That the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50785:17"/>Liberal Man deviſeth Liberal things; and by Liberal things he ſhall ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now can the <hi>Teſt</hi> againſt the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> be properly called a <hi>Liberal thing,</hi> when it is a thing that keeps them out of their ſhare of the Government, on the account of <hi>Conſcience?</hi> Here is neither ſtanding by <hi>Faith,</hi> nor ſtanding by <hi>Liberal things:</hi> Which is the moſt Liberal thing, think ye, a firm <hi>Magna Charta</hi> to ſecure every Man in his Chriſtian and Civil Liberty, which his Majeſty does propoſe to be deviſed by the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Nation in Parliament, or this Old long Parliamentary <hi>Teſt?</hi> Truly for my part, I cannot ſee any kind of Liberality in the <hi>Teſt;</hi> and I can ſee no kind of nigard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Churliſhneſs that there can be in a firm <hi>Magna Charta</hi> for our <hi>Chriſtian Liberty:</hi> Thus you ſee theſe two holy Apoſtles were both for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> and to make <hi>Faith</hi> their <hi>Test</hi> to ſtand upon, and ſo am I; not but that I am for all the Civil Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that can be made, which does not tye up Mens Conſciences in point of <hi>Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty:</hi> I am not for knocking men in the head, or ruining them, becauſe they are not of my Principle; but let the Tares grow with the Wheat, until the great Harveſt; and whoſoever is not of this Mind, is no Chriſtian, let him call himſelf what he pleaſe: And I do not doubt, but there are Honeſt, Able Heads and Hearts at work, a draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to themſelves Propoſitions for the Eſtabliſhing of our <hi>Christian Liberty,</hi> againſt the time that the Great and Honourable Counſel of the Land ſhall meet together, that will be ſatisfactory to all the honeſt Hearts that are willing to be ſatisfied: Thus you ſee alſo, that thoſe that had rather that all the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts</hi> ſhould be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then that one <hi>Teſt</hi> againſt the Romaniſts ſhould be taken away and Aboliſhed, do chooſe rather to ſin againſt God now, then to venture to ſuffer hereafter, becauſe the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Sacramental Teſt</hi> are Eſſentially ſinful in themſelves, as you ſee clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthfly,</hi> Is it ſo that Men muſt Eat and Drink their own Damnation to qualify them, before ever they can be admitted to come into the Government, or any place of Truſt and Profit? Why then this clearly Informs us, that poor Deluded Men, that do Obey theſe Laws, do pawn that precious Jewel, even their Souls, in the Hands of the Devil; and do chooſe rather to truſt the Devil with their Souls, then to truſt God with their Eſtates, or to give Wicked Men an advantage againſt them, of bringing them into 500 <hi>l.</hi> Damage; and none but Chriſt, whom they do thus Crucify, can Redeem them out of <hi>Satans</hi> Hands; and that by his precious Blood, in appeaſing the Wrath of God, and attoning them to God, by giving them Unfeigned Repentance and Faith in him; for none can come to God, but in and through him alone; the Lord of his Infinite Mercy awake ye all to Unfeigned Repentance, before the Decree bringeth forth; for if Death cuts you down in this Impenitent Condition, you have no better hopes of Eſcaping the Damnation of Hell, nor of Enjoying Eternal Happineſs in Heaven, then this, which is a Dreadful deceitful one, as you will find when it is too late.</p>
            <p>Namely, That the Word of God is not true; which is in plain Engliſh, without the help of Hebrew, Greek or Latin, to hope that God is a <hi>Lyar;</hi> but <hi>let God be True, and every Man a Lyar,</hi> 3 <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. O Horrible! Horrible! Poor Deluded Sonls! That ever there ſhould be ſuch a Device of the Devil promoted by Men, for to Damn Men's Souls by Law! What will after Ages think of ſuch a Generation of Men as this? O! that ever it ſhould enter into the Hearts of Rational Men, to make ſuch a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-Daring Law as this! And that which encreaſeth the wonder, is this, That there ſhould be ſo many Pillars of their Church, which are called Spiritual Lords; and that ever they ſhould conſent to it, that ought to have told thoſe Gentlemen that promoted it, the Danger and Evil of it, for had they had any Honour for God, and Value and Eſteem for Chriſt and his Ordinance, and Pity for Men's Souls, they would never have
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50785:17"/>made their Church Door ſo much wider then our Saviour Chriſt and his Apoſtles made it, or then their own 19th Article made it; to make the Church of God not only a Den of Robbers in his ſight, but alſo to make it a Herd of Swine: And is this to ſeparate the Precious from the Vile? I think the Church of <hi>England</hi> ought not to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue her ſelf upon ſuch Laws as theſe are, above their Neighbours; and truly ſhe hath little cauſe to make her boaſt of theſe Laws and Teſts, which ſhould rather be matter of ſhame unto them indeed, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.14. <hi>I have ſeen alſo in the Prophets of</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem <hi>an horrible thing; they commit Adultery, and walk in Lies; they ſtreng then alſo the Hands of evil doers, that none doth return from his wickedneſs; they are all unto me as</hi> Sodom, <hi>and the Inhabitants as</hi> Gomorah: Therefore the ſame Judgments that God brought upon theſe Prophets that was ſo guilty then, may be expected to come upon thoſe Prophets among us now, or an Equivalent, who are guilty of the ſame ſins, if not worſe; for if the Body of Sin and Iniquity now, be of the ſame ſhape and big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as it was then, why then a Garment of Wrath and Vengeance of the ſame ſize now, will fit it as did then, therefore look for it, and expect it; without a ſpeedy Repentance, there will be a ſpeedy Riddance, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.13, 14. <hi>For from the leaſt of them, to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of them, every one is given to Covetouſneſs; and from the Prophet, even unto the Prieſt, every one dealeth falſly. They have healed alſo the Hurt of the Daughter of my People ſlightly, ſaying, Peace, Peace, when there is no Peace.</hi> Were they aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when they had committed Abomination? Nay, they were not at all aſhamed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could they Bluſh; Therefore, <hi>They ſhall fall among them that fall, at the time that I viſit them: they ſhall be caſt down,</hi> ſaith the Lord. Thus you ſee what a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Condition all they are in, that are thus guilty now among us; they are nothing of Kin to their own <hi>19th Article.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> This informs us alſo, that all thoſe that do thus come into the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Inveſted with theſe God-provoking, moſt abominable Qualifications, do Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure up Wrath againſt the day of Wrath, and Revelation of God's Righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, without a ſpeedy and unfained Repentance, and turning to God; They do eat and drink their own Spiritual Bane, and poyſon and deſtroy their own Souls. And, <hi>What ſhall it profit a Man to gain the whole World, and loſe his own Soul?</hi> Or, <hi>What ſhall be given in Exchange for his Soul?</hi> Saith our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. Pray Gentlemen, try your ſelves by theſe things.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Eighthly,</hi> Is it ſo, that all thoſe that come into the Government, Qualified according to the Sacramental Law, <hi>Do Eat and Drink their own Damnation;</hi> then this informs us, that this Law, is againſt the Statute, ſtanding, unalterable Law of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: And our own Fundamental Law of the Land ſaith, That whatſoever Laws are made againſt the Law of God, are <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> void and null in themſelves, and therefore not to be regarded, nor taken notice of, no further than to loath it, and to abhor it, and deſtroy it: And thoſe Spiritual Gentlemen, that had their Hands and Hearts en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in the making of theſe Laws, are the moſt to blame of all, and the Blood of their Souls, that have periſhed upon this Account, will be required at their Hands; <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Again, when a Righteous Man doth turn from his Righteouſneſs, and commit Iniquity, and I lay a ſtumbling Block before him, he ſhall die in his Sin; and his Righteouſneſs, which he hath done, ſhall not be remembred: But his Blood will I require at thine Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſome will Object, That no Man is forc'd to come into the Government, and ſo no man is forc'd to receive the Sacrament on this Account. But if they will come into the Government, they muſt receive it: You ſay, no body is forc'd to come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Government; though, if I miſtake not, as I am confident I do not, there is a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50785:18"/>Law in being, to force all Adult Perſons to the Sacrament, once a year at leaſt, at their Pariſh-Church; or elſe, Pray, Why do they receive Three pence a Head, for every Adult Perſon in your Family, and have put Perſons in the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> for not paying of it? But that by the By.</p>
            <p>Pray tell me, Is there not an abſolute neceſſity of Government? Why, yes; no Man denies that, for it is an Ordinance of God; why, if ſo, then it follows, that there is as abſolute a neceſſity, for Perſons to come into the Government: Here you do own, that there is an abſolute Neceſſity of Government, and that from the moſt ſolid Ground and Reaſon that can be; namely, becauſe it is an Ordinance of God; and therefore it follows, that there is an abſolute Neceſſity of Perſons, to govern well: What then? Can it ever be imagined, that God hath Ordained, that any Man ſhould Damn his Soul, to partake of this Ordinance of God, namely, the Civil Government? For you ſee clearly, as this old way of governing by <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> now ſtands, no Man can come into it, nor be rightly qualified for it, before he hath been and Crucified to himſelf, the Son of God afreſh, and put him to an open ſhame: And alſo, Eat and Drink Damnation to himſelf, not diſcerning the Lord's Body; ſo that this is the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Conſequence of that Argument, <hi>viz.</hi> That whoſoever will partake of God's Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the Civil Government, muſt firſt, Murder our Saviour Chriſt Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally; and alſo, Murder his own Soul Hypocritically: And alſo it follows, That there is an abſolute Neceſſity of it too, by the former Aſſertion; namely, the Laws and Ordinance of God, and the Laws of Men; or elſe Perſons muſt ſin againſt God, by not obeying that Ordinance of his Appointment: And then, the Conſequence that would follow, muſt be this, That there muſt be no Government at all: So that it is brought to this Point, either they muſt Crucifie Chriſt, and Eat and Drink their own Damnation, or elſe there muſt be no Government among us at all. And what would the World be without Government? It would be a meer Shambles: For there is a great deal of Difficulty, to keep People to rights, where there is good Government; and how much more difficult would it be, to keep themſelves within bounds, if there was no Government? Who ſhould keep them? Or ſay, to him that is ſtronger than himſelf, What doſt thou? Now the Merciful God, who delighteth in Mercy, who is a God of Order, and not of Confuſion, that hath ordained Civil Government, never ordained ſuch a cruel, baſe, foul way, to come into it: You do tacitly make God a cruel Task-Maſter, ſeverer than <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that would make the People to make Brick without Straw, and yet abate nothing of the Tale, which is, to make God the Author of Evil, and ſo <hi>charge God fooliſhly:</hi> Surely God that made this Ordinance of Civil Government, never did ſhut it up, and incloſed it, ſo as there is no coming at it, or into it, without Crucifying his own Eternal Son afreſh, and putting him to an open Shame; and to Eat and Drink their own Damnation, which is, to make God the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of one of the greateſt Sins that ever was committed, and ſo to charge God fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhly; for by this Crucifying Soul-Damning-Law, they incloſe God's Field, namely, his Ordinance of Civil Government, and ſtop up the way to it, and will not allow God a way to his own Ground: The Law of the Land, alloweth every man a way to his ground, and will you not allow God a way to his? And is not this a miſerable Caſe &amp; Condition, for a People or Nation to be in, that you muſt either have no Government at all, or elſe it muſt be made up of a Company of Men, that have pawned their Souls in the Hands of the Devil; one or the other it muſt be? And which is the worſt of theſe, I will leave the Reader to Conſider; whether to have no Government, or to have it made up of ſuch deſperate Hypocrites as all they muſt be, that cometh into the Government, in the full Latitude of its Required Qualifications? They muſt be the Enemies of God, and of all good People, and their own Enemies alſo; For muſt they not be God's
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50785:18"/>Enemies that do vertually Murder his own Son; when it is ſaid in Scripture, <hi>He that hates his Brother, is a Murderer.</hi> And muſt they not be good Mens Enemies, that would compel them to do the like with themſelves? And muſt they not be their own Enemies, that Deſtroy and Murder their own Souls? And all this is done in the very Act of Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; ſo that you ſee this Objection is altogether groundleſs, as well as very dangerous; for when our Enemies ſhall have the ſole Legiſlative Power lodged wholly in their own Hands, what is it that they may not do? If God does permit them, they may make Laws to cut the reſt of the Subjects Throats, and yet not ſo Cruel as this Law is, to Crucifie the Son of God, that ſhould be their Redeemer, and Eat and Drink their own Damnation; which is to deſtoy their own Souls, without God's Inſinite preventing Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, before they can be duly qualifyed to come into the Government; Aye, or to live in the Nation, if they are Adult Perſons, becauſe there is a Law in being, that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces all ſo to do it; but indeed, many Perſons does do by our Lord and Saviour, as <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi>'s Butler did by <hi>Joſeph,</hi> when the King reſtored him again to be his Cup-bearer, he ſoon forgot <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Kindneſs, and <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Affliction too: Why, even ſo it is now with ſome few of the Multitude, that have been Sufferers and Priſoners with Chriſt in the late Horrible Perſecutions: Now they are ſet at Liberty, and are at Eaſe, they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the Bleſſed Jeſus, as the Butler forgot <hi>Joſeph,</hi> until he had occaſion to make uſe of him, for Chriſt is ſtill in Sufferings Vertually, and lieth Crucified among us, and will be, until theſe Crucifying Laws be Aboliſhed; which if they be continued, will indanger the Deſtruction of the Nation, by ſome Tremendous Sweeping Judgment, from the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Hand of God; and therefore it is the Duty, as well as the Intereſt of all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, good and bad, of what Perſwaſion ſoever, to joyn Heart and Hand with his Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Majeſty in the Repealing of them, that thoſe Judgments may be Diverted, that ſeems to threaten us, and will Inevitably come upon us.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Ninthly,</hi> Is it ſo that theſe Laws, while they are in being, do Crucifie Jeſus Chriſt, the Son of God, afreſh, and put him to an open ſhame? Then this may inform us, That the Nation lieth now under a worſe Plague, then the Plague of Peſtilence; for a Nation or People may have the Plague of Peſtilence, which the Lord keep from us, which I fear will come without Unfeigned Repentance, where they may not be guilty of ſo great a Sin, as to have Chriſt Crucified among them, and Expoſed to an open ſhame by them. His Gracious Majeſty, by his Healing Declaration, has Cured his Poor Subjects of this Contagious Diſeaſe, the Plague of Suffering: As to the effects of it, by theſe <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> it is Cured as to what is in our Fleſh and Clothes, <hi>Levit.</hi> 13. <hi>But yet it is in the Plaiſtering and Stones and Timber of the Houſe ſtill, Levit.</hi> 14.44, 45. <hi>Then the Prieſt ſhall come and look, and behold, if the Plague be ſpread in the Houſe, it is a fretting Leproſie in the Houſe; it is unclean, and he ſhall break down the Houſe, and the Stones of it, and the Timber thereof, and all the Morter of the Houſe; and he ſhall carry them forth out of the City, into an unclean place:</hi> So let every Man, good and bad, ſay of all theſe Spiritual <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> that are made againſt Mens Principles; Let this Unclean Houſe, that has this fretting Leproſie in the very Plaiſtering and Walls and Stones and Timber thereof, all be broke down and carried out into the Body of a Bill of Abolition, and Buried in the Grave of Abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for ever. O! Sirs, leave not a Horn nor Hoof of this Unclean Beaſt behind, do not plead for this, or that, or t'other, to be continued; but if you will prevent the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God from coming unto you, why then take Chriſt down from the Croſs, and be reconciled unto him, and make your Peace with him, for it is he that you have been Crucifying all this while, that muſt ſave you if ever you are ſaved. O! <hi>Kiſs the Son, leſt he be angry, and ye periſh from the way when his wrath is kindled but a little; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are all they that put their Truſt in him,</hi> Pſal. 2.12.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:50785:19"/>
            <p>Again, <hi>Tenthly,</hi> Is it ſo, that none can come into the Government, unleſs they be qualified according to the ſeveral Unjuſt Laws in that caſe provided, although they be againſt the great Charter of Heaven, and againſt the Fundamental Laws of the Land, and againſt their own 19th Article of Definition, and againſt the Principles of the very Light and Law of Nature, but that they muſt firſt Crucifie their Maker, that ſhould be their Husband and Redeemer, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.5. <hi>For thy Maker is thine Husband [the Lord of Hoſts is his Name] and thy Redeemer the holy one of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>the God of the whole Earth ſhall he be called.</hi> Do you ſee, my Friends, what a Friend to Mankind you do thus abuſe? The beſt Friend that ever Sinful Man had. And they muſt Pawn or Mortgage their Souls into the Hands of the Devil, before they can be admitted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; then this Informs us of the Abſolute Neceſſity, and the Indiſpenſible Duty, for honeſt good Men of all ſorts to come into the Goyernment, and to deſtroy all the Works of the Devil. Namely, To Aboliſh for ever all theſe Sinful Laws and Teſts, that are againſt all Mens Conſciences in meer Matters of Religion; and let us all do as we would be done by; is it ever to be imagined, that men of ſuch Vicious Profligate Lives and Ungodly Plundering Principles, which cannot govern their own Conſciences, can be fit to govern other Peoples, who ſtick at nothing, but will Crucifie their Maker, if he ſtands between them and Worldly Preferment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eleventhly</hi> and Laſtly, Is it ſo, that Perſons muſt Crucifie their Maker, the Son of God, and Pawn that Precious Jewel, their Soul, by Eating and Drinking their own Damnation in the Hands of the Devil? Then hence we may be Informed, that this old Government, which is founded upon <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Tests</hi> in meer Matters of Religion and Conſcience, lieth in the hands of the Wicked One, namely, the Prince of <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> as the old Wicked World before the Flood did, and therefore the Deſtruction of it in ſome ſence will be like unto that; for mind <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.6. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Wicked he ſhall Rain Snares, Fire and Brimſtone, and an horrible Tempeſt: This ſhall be the Portion of their Cup.</hi> God Rains down a Flood of Snares of their own making upon them, they have been making of them, off and on, about 120 years, a little more or leſs; and now God is Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own Snares upon them; that is, upon the old Government, and the old Spirit of Perſecution, as Gods Spirit did ſtrive with the old World; and as God, provided an Ark by <hi>Noah</hi> to ſave all his Family, why even ſo God, by his Majeſty, has provided an Ark for all his Good Subjects: <hi>For a ſmall moment have I forſaken thee, but with great Mercies will I gather thee; in a little Wrath I hid my Face from thee for a moment, but with everlaſting Kindneſs will I have Mercy on thee, ſaith the Lord thy Redeemer, for this is as the Waters of</hi> Noah <hi>unto me; for as I have ſworn that the Waters of</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah <hi>ſhould no more go over the Earth; ſo have I ſworn that I would not be wroth with thee, nor Rebuke thee;</hi> that is, for the Preſervation of Gods People. And here is the Deſtruction of the Snare-makers, aluding to <hi>Noah</hi>'s Flood, alſo, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.17, 18, 19. <hi>Fear, and the Pit, and the Snare are upon thee; O Inhabitant of the Earth: And it ſhall come to paſs, that he who fleeth from the noiſe of the fear, ſhall fall into the Pit; and he that cometh up out of the midſt of the Pit, ſhall be taken in the Snare; for the Windows from on high are open, and the Foundations of the Earth do ſhake; the Earth is utterly broken down, the Earth is clean diſſolved, the Earth is moved exceedingly.</hi> Now in the 7 <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.12. there you have this 11 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. and this 24 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 18. taken by way of Alluſion, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. This is Metaphorically, and not Literally and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly meant; nor of the End of the World, for the 13 <hi>Verſe</hi> may convince any man of that; but this old way of Governing will paſs away with a very great Noiſe, and this Element wherein the Spirit of Perſecution does live and breathe, will be melted, and the Generation of Perſecuters muſt paſs away; this old corrupt Leven, both in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50785:19"/>Church and State, muſt be Purged out; <hi>All Old things muſt be done away, and all things muſt become New;</hi> Pſal. 102.25, 26. <hi>Yea, all of them ſhall wax Old like a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; as a Vesture ſhalt thou change them, and they ſhall be changed.</hi> Thus you ſee this old way of Government, ſo far as it conſiſteth in Sinful <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> lieth in the Hands of <hi>Satars;</hi> and theſe poor deluded Souls, that are contending for it, for Perſecutions ſake, are his Bond-ſlaves; they are taken Captive at his Will, and the Diſſenters are in Captivity to them, and theſe Laws alſo. So that in Effect, we are all in Captivity; and them that are for this Sacramental Teſt, by which they muſt <hi>Eat and Drink Damnation to themſelves,</hi> are in the greateſt Captivity of all: So that it will be a greater Mercy to them, for to have all theſe Yokes and Snares of the Devil broken, than to any other Perſons whatſoever, though indeed it will be a very great Mercy to the whole Nation.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Secondly</hi> and <hi>Laſtly,</hi> I am come to an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Exhortation,</hi> which ſhall be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to two ſorts of Perſons: The firſt ſhall be, unto all them that were <hi>Sacramental Teſt-Makers,</hi> and <hi>Teſt-Givers,</hi> and <hi>Teſt-Takers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort of Perſons, that I ſhall direct my Exhortation and Counſel unto, ſhall be, unto all them that are for the continuing of theſe <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> for fear of Popery prevailing upon us: And theſe are ſuch, as are not of a perſecuting Spirit.</p>
            <p>You ſee, I have ſearched into this deſperate Wound, or Plague of <hi>Leproſie;</hi> and I find it to be very dangerous and contagious. It is gotten into the <hi>Plaiſter</hi> and <hi>Stones,</hi> and into the very <hi>Timber of the Houſe;</hi> and therefore under God, I will preſcribe a <hi>Healing Plaister,</hi> and a <hi>Sovereign Antidote,</hi> for the making it a perfect Cure; I would not leave your Wounds open, and a bleeding. Now they are ſearched into, I will not leave the worſt of you, without Hopes of obtaining Pardoning Mercy, in the <hi>Blood of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt</hi> of all, In the firſt place, I Exhort you all, in the Name of my Great Lord and Maſter, <hi>By whom Kings Reign, and Princes Decree Juſtice;</hi> eſpecially, you that have been <hi>Sacramental Test-Makers,</hi> and <hi>Teſt-Givers,</hi> and alſo <hi>Teſt-Takers,</hi> that are guilty of <hi>Crucifying the Son of God afreſh;</hi> and putting him to an open Shame, and <hi>Eating and Drinking your own Damnation,</hi> or <hi>Condemnation,</hi> to repent from the bottom of your Hearts: Look upon him whom you have Crucified, and Mourn over him, and be in bitterneſs of Soul, as <hi>one is in bitterneſs for his Firſt-born.</hi> O Sirs! Be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to expel the deadly Spiritual Poyſon, which you have ſwallowed down; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the <hi>Sacramental Test,</hi> by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfained Repentance,</hi> or it will kindle a Fire in you, that will burn to the loweſt Hell; for there is a Death and Damnation too, in that Cup, for all the impenitent Partakers of it; for as it is a Cup of Conſolation, and Salvation to the People of God; ſo it is a Cup of Spiritual Poyſon and Damnation, to Carnal Prophane Hypocrites, which are but Spiritual Vermine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I Exhort you, to Repent of all your ill-gotten plundered Goods, and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them up again alſo, by reſtoring it again unto them, from whom you took it: I mean, in that way that His Majeſty hath appointed under God; and God hath ſaid, <hi>Ye ſhall do it,</hi> Job 20.15, 18. <hi>He hath ſwallowed down Riches, and he ſhall vomit them up again; God ſhall caſt them out of his Belly. That which he laboured for, ſhall he Restore;</hi> that is, they laboured for it, in a wrong illegal way; as we uſe to ſay, <hi>Prank more labour than Thank, who required it at their Hands;</hi> according to his Subſtance, ſhall the Reſtitution be, and he ſhall not rejoice therein. It may be you will ſay, <hi>You had a Law on your ſide:</hi> Why! So the old Gang of <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> could boaſt of a <hi>Law,</hi> they had on their ſide, by which they did literally and wickedly Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50785:20"/>our Lord and Saviour. <hi>We have a Law, and by our Law, this Man ought to die:</hi> And here is a Law of the very ſame Complection of yours, if not Prophetically ſpoken of the ſame, in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.1, 2. With a Wo pronounced againſt the Legiſlators thereof, <hi>Wo unto them that Decree <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteous Decrees, and that write Grievouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which they have Preſcribed: To turn aſide the needy from Judgment, and to take away the Right from the, poor of my People; that Widows may be their Prey, and that they may Rob the Fatherleſs,</hi> Here you ſee a Law made againſt God's People; And thoſe that make ſuch Laws as theſe are, are Perſons that have no Communion, or Fellowſhip with God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.20, 23. <hi>Shall the Throne of Iniquity have Fellowſhip with thee, which frameth Miſchief by a Law?</hi> Pray mark, What will be the End of ſuch? <hi>And he ſhall bring upon them their own Iniquity, and ſhall cut them off in their own Wickedneſs: Yea, the Lord our God ſhall cut them off.</hi> Pſal. 7.15, 16. <hi>He made a Pit, and digged it, and is fallen into the Ditch which he made. His Miſchief ſhall return upon his own Head, and his violent dealing ſhall come down upon his own Pate.</hi> That is, God does bring it down upon them, which is a fulfilling the Words of our Saviour, who hath ſaid, <hi>That the ſame Meaſure ye make, ſhall be made unto you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain:</hi> O Sirs! I beſeech ye to take ſhame to your ſelves, before the Lord, for all your Abominations; that you may not be put to ſhame by the Lord: Eye the juſt Hand of God in all theſe Great Providences: <hi>Humble your ſelves in Duſt and Aſhes, Acknowledge and Confeſs all your Sins, and break off from Sin by Righteouſneſs; and cry mightily to God for pardoning Mercy, in the Blood and Merits of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be, or I hope at leaſt-wiſe, that ſome of ye will ſay, I am guilty of all theſe Abominations, and of Multitudes more; I have been a ſierce Perſecuter, a Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, and an Injurious Perſon; I have been a Whoremonger, a Drunkard, and a Lier; and I have often Crucified the Son of God, and made his Wounds bleed afreſh, and put him to an open Shame, <hi>by Eating and Drinking unworthily at the Lord's Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi> and I have had a hand in Impriſoning, and Impoveriſhing the Saints and Servants of God, by which means, ſome of them have periſhed in ſtinking naſty Goals; and is there any Hopes of pardoning Mercy, for ſuch a horrible Sinner as I am? Yes, I tell thee in the Name of God, <hi>who is a God that delighteth in Mercy;</hi> if thou doſt ask this Queſtion in good earneſt, I tell thee from God's own Word, that there is hopes of Mercy for thee, Dear Soul, if thou do from the bottom of thy Heart, confeſs and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thy Sins, and turn to God, and believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: <hi>Kiſs the Son leaſt he be angry with ye, and ye periſh from the Way, when his Wrath is kindled but a little.</hi> And Pray for your Encouragement, Read and Conſider well of the <hi>1st</hi> of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 16, 17, 18, 19, 20. And <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.6, 7, 8.9. <hi>Seek ye the Lord, while he may be found; call ye upon him while he is near, Let the Wicked forſake his way, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteout Man his Thoughts; and let him return unto the Lord, and he will have Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon him; and to our God, for he will abundantly pardon: For my Thoughts are not your Thoughts, neither are your Ways, my Ways, ſaith the Lord. For as the Heavens are higher than the Earth, ſo are my Ways higher than your Ways; and my Thoughts, than your Thoughts:</hi> With Reverence be it ſpoken, What can the Lord ſay more unto you, for your Encouragement, to caſt your ſelves upon his pardoning Mercy, and Free Grace? For there is more Vertue and Merit, in the leaſt drop of Chriſt's Blood, to pardon and ſave you, then there is Malignity in all your Sins, to damn and deſtroy you, if you will but believe in Chriſt, and come unto him, and reſign up the Government and Conduct of your Souls unto him; for he calls <hi>the weary and heavy-laden Sinners unto him,</hi> and promiſes <hi>to give them Reſt, Matth.</hi> 11.28, 29, 30. Nothing but Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief and Deſpair can with-hold God's Merciful Hard, from Extending Pardoning
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50785:20"/>Grace unto you. It is not the Greatneſs, nor the Hainouſneſs, nor the Multitudes of your Sins that can hinder Pardoning Mercy from you, if your own Unbelief do not: And I will not ſpeak without Book, but I will give you ſeveral Inſtances of as Vile Perſons as ever you have been, if not Viler, that have been Pardoned and Saved, that are left upon Record in the holy Scripture, as Monuments of Gods Infinite Mercy and Free Grace. But let me give you this Precaution, that you do not preſume upon Gods Mercy, to go on any longer and further into Sin: You muſt not continue in Sin, that Grace may abound; God forbid, that ever you ſhould make ſuch an evil uſe of it, to turn the Grace of God into Laſciviouſneſs; but it is that you may not deſpair and pine away in your own Iniquity, nor go any further on this Black Score. And the firſt Perſon that I ſhall Inſtance in, ſhall be <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> who was a Cruel Bloody Idolater, as you may read, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. and yet notwithſtanding all that, <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> Repented, and was Pardoned and Saved, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.12, 13. <hi>And when he was in affliction, he beſought the Lord his God, and humbled himſelf greatly before the God of his Fathers, and prayed unto him, and he was intreated of him, and heard his ſupplication, and brought him again to</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>into his Kingdom; then</hi> Manaſſeh <hi>knew that the Lord he was God.</hi> He never knew God until he was Converted; no nor no other Sinner does neither, let him have what Notional Knowledge he will in his Head, if he have not Sanctifying Saving Grace in his Heart. It is ſaid, That <hi>Manaſſeb</hi> made the Streets of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to run with Blood as Water, and cauſed his own Children to paſs through the Fire, and was guilty of Witchcraft and Idolatry, and other Hainous Sins; his Sins reached as high as Heaven, yet Gods Mercy being higher than the Heavens, that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looked all his Sins, and God caſt them behind his Back, and blotted them out of his Book, and drowned all his Spiritual <hi>Aegyptians</hi> in the <hi>Red-Sea</hi> of Chriſt's Blood, and did pardon and ſave him. What doſt thou think now, Dear Soul? Haſt thou any room left to deſpair of the Mercies of God?</p>
            <p>A ſecond Inſtance is that of Perſecuting <hi>Saul,</hi> whom God in Infinite Mercy Pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and made a Preaching and Praying Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> afterward, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.3, 4, 5, 11. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.14, 14, 15. There <hi>Paul</hi> acknowledged the free Grace of God, in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning of him who was before a Blaſphemer, and a Perſecuter, and an Injurious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Acts</hi> 22.4. There he confeſſed himſelf a Bloody Perſecutor; yet as Vile as he was, all his Sins were pardoned in the Blood of Chriſt. A third Inſtance of Gods free Grace and Pardoning Mercy in the Blood of Chriſt, was that of the Cruel ſturdy Jaylor, <hi>Acts</hi> 16. And a fourth Inſtance of Gods Pardoning of moſt notorious Vile Sinners, that was found Guilty of that filthy notorious Bed-Roll of the Sin of <hi>Sodomy</hi> and <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi> and <hi>Whoredom,</hi> and <hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> and <hi>Theft,</hi> is in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10, 11. <hi>And ſuch were ſome of you, but ye are waſhed, but ye are ſanctified, but ye are juſtified in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God.</hi> And there was <hi>Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen,</hi> a very hainous Sinner, yet ſhe was waſhed in the Blood of the Lamb of God, that taketh away Sin, and ſhe was made a precious Saint. And there was ſome of them very Perſons that had their Hands Imbrued in Chriſt's Blood, we read on in the Acts of the Apoſtles, yet they were waſhed in Chriſts Blood, and pardoned in his Merits, and ſaved by his Grace: Thus you ſee, here is encouragement enough for the Vileſt of Men, that have been Sacramental Myſtical Crucifiers of Chriſt, and Perſecuters, and Whoremongers, and Drunkards, and Thieves, and Idolaters, to come unto Chriſt for Pardoning-Grace and Mercy. <hi>And whoſoever doth ſo come to Chriſt while he is upon the Mercy-Seat, He hath ſaid that He will in no wiſe caſt out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I Exuort all you that were <hi>Teſt</hi> Makers, and <hi>Teſt</hi> Givers, and <hi>Teſt</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers in this Sacramental way and manner; not to flatter your ſelves with the hopes of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50785:21"/>ever getting that Predominating Perſecuting Power again: But be contented with your ſhare and proportion of the Government, with all other free Denniſons of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> that have every whit as much and juſt Right unto it as your ſelves; remember Covetouſeeſs is the Root of all Evil, God will not truſt you with the ſole Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Government of the Nation any longer, to be a Scourge to your honeſt peaceable Neighbours, <hi>Nahum</hi> 1.7, 8, 9. <hi>The Lord is good, a ſtrong hold in the day of trouble, and he knoweth them that truſt in him; But with an overflowing flood he will make an utter end of the place thereof, and Darkneſs ſhall purſue his Enemies. What do ye imagine againſt the Lord? He will make an utter end, affliction ſhall not riſe up the ſecond time.</hi> God is ſpeaking this unto us at this time, as I Humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, by his Anointed Servant, the Kings Majeſty; for he ſaith, <hi>That he is reſolved to make an utter end of all Perſecuting Penal Laws and Tests whatſoever; and that they ſhall not riſe up a ſecond time to afflict his Subjects any more.</hi> And God is a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing his Perſecuting Enemies at this time, in this dark Providence and Diſpenſation to them, by the Juſt Proceedings of his Gracious Majeſty, in calling them to an account for all the Moneys and Goods which they have taken from the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> of all ſorts, of late years; and he is giving them a Purge and a Vomit too, which God hath prepared in his Word for all them that have this foul Stomach. O! Sirs, do not ſtrive to be Rampant, and Exalt your ſelves above your Neighbours, and to get the Whip in your hands again, for God will not truſt ſuch Unjuſt Stewards as you have been, with ſo great a Betruſtment; But God is a calling you to an Account for your Stewardſhip, for you may no longer be Stewards, for now your Stewardſhip is ended, as to Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, your Account for Plundering beginneth; <hi>the Robbery of the Wicked ſhall deſtroy them, becauſe they refuſe to do Judgment.</hi> O! Sirs, do not Delude your ſelves, for it is the Juſt Lord, that loveth Righteouſneſs, and that hateth Robbery for Burnt-Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that does all theſe things; Do you not ſee that God is calling you to an Account for your Violence done to himſelf; for as he that Perſecutes Chriſt's Flock, Perſecutes Chriſt himſelf; ſo alſo they that Rob God's People, Robs God himſelf, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Ye are Curſed with a Curſe, for ye have Robbed me; even this whole Nation.</hi> This was ſpoken to the Jews; for he that toucheth Gods People by Violence, doth touch the Apple of Gods Eye by Wickedneſs, <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.8. And God hath ſent his Servant unto you that ſpoiled his People, to call you to an Account for it. O! Friends, I beſeech ye to Eye the Juſt Hand of God in all this, for until then you cannot make a right Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of theſe great Providences, as you ought to do, and Juſtifie God, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn your ſelves; and do not entertain hard Thoughts of his Servant, which is the Inſtrument in his Hand by which he doth it, for it is. God that does all theſe things; it is he that putteth down one, and ſeueth up another: Theſe great things does not come by luck or chance, Affliction it ſelf does not riſe up out of the Duſt; for if a Sparrow that is but of half a Farthing Price, cannot fall to the Ground without Gods Providence, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.29, 30, Much leſs can ſuch wonderful great Providences and Diſpenſations as we have ſeen, and yet ſhall further ſee come without the Hand of our Heavenly Fathers putting it into the King, his Servants Heart, to do it among us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.6, 7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>For Promotion cometh neither from the Eaſt, nor from the Weſt, nor from the South; But God is the Judge, he putteth down one, and ſetteth up another; for in the Hand of the Lord there is a Cup, and the Wine is Red, and full of Mixture, and he poureth out of the ſame; but the Dregs thereof, all the Wicked of the Earth ſhall wring them out, and Drink them. But I will dealare for ever, I will Sing Praiſes to the God of</hi> Jacob; <hi>all the Horns of the Wicked alſo will I cut off.</hi> That is, All their Perſecuting Power and Strength. But the People of God, <hi>viz.</hi> That is,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:50785:21"/>all them that truly feareth God, and worketh Righteouſneſs, their Horn ſhall be Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. O Sirs! Do not you that are of a perſecuting Spirit, imagine, that God will ever permit you to get up unto your Old Trade of Plundering, and Spoiling, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Havock of the Churches again; after ſo great a Rebuke from Heaven, for thoſe many Heaven-daring Abominations, that you are, and have been Guilty of; do but conſider well, what you have been doing: <hi>For you have been Plowing Iniquity, and ſowing Wickedneſs;</hi> and therefore, <hi>now you muſt Reap Shame and Contempt:</hi> For the Hand of the Lord is lifted up againſt the Spirit of Perſecution, and is falling upon it, whether you will ſee it or no. But the Word ſaith, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.11. <hi>Ye ſhall ſee, and be aſhamed, for your Envy at the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I beſeech you not to murmur, nor Repine againſt God, for all his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential Dealings towards you; neither do you entertain a hard Thought of his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed Servant the King, for his Obedience to God, in giving and granting this Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Chriſtian Liberty unto us all, without Exceptions, or Reſtrictions in Matters of meer Religion and Conſcience, which is ſuch a Jewel, that it is a none-ſuch upon Earth: It is the juſtifiableſt thing that ever was done by any Earthly Prince, the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Effects of which, the Generations to come will richly ſhare in, and have Cauſe to Bleſs and Praiſe God for it: Let all the Enemies to it, ſay what they pleaſe, there can be no Preſident found for this Gracious Proceedings of His Majeſty, from all former Ages, cloathed with all its Circumſtances; therefore let not our Enemies murmur at it, but be perſwaded to ſubmit unto God, and lay their Mouths in the Duſt; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that their Puniſhment for their Perſecution, and all other Abominations that does attend that curſed Spirit, as Servants to it, is leſs then they deſerve: But now God's Righteous Judgments are in the Earth, a reckoning with the Men of Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Perſecuting Principles, let the Inhabitants thereof learn Righteouſneſs, and do not be thus ſtriving againſt the Stream; for I will aſſure ye, with Submiſſion to God, it will be but in vain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I Exhort all you of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to be ſatisfied and willing that all other Free-born <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Men ſhould enjoy their Birth-rights in common with you in the Government; and do not think, that you have any wrong done ye; I know no ſuch excellent Vertue that there is in you, above all other <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Men: Indeed it is ſaid, <hi>That the Righteous Man is more excellent than his Neighbour:</hi> But I cannot think, how ſuch as have been Perſecuters and Snare-makers can be ſuch; but ſay they, <hi>We have the Laws of our ſide:</hi> Why, that is true; but I hope by this time you are convinced, that you have little cauſe to boaſt of them, or value your ſelves upon them Laws that you have on your ſide, that Exalts you above your Neighbours, they being the moſt of them of ſuch a Nature, as the Devil himſelf, if he had any ſhame in him, would even bluſh, and be aſhamed of them. For my part, I know not one Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Law that the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath, above all other People; for they have Laws to perſecute Chriſt tacitly and conſequentially, and fight againſt God: Ay, and they have a Law to Crucifie Chriſt too, Myſtically and Sacramentally, as has been proved: And ſhall any ſober Man of Sence value himſelf, upon ſuch God-provoking Laws as theſe are, that the Turkiſh <hi>Alcaron</hi> can no way match?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> My Dear Countrey-Men, pray be perſwaded not to value your ſelves upon a Law that is the Myſtical Croſs, on which our Lord and Saviour is Sacramentally Crucified: And do not make a God to rely on, of ſuch Diabolical Stuff as theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Crucifying Laws are: But be perſwaded to part with theſe, and get better in the room of them, in a Bill of Abolition; for worſe you cannot have; And then you may expect God's Bleſſing upon them, and God's Protection by them, when
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50785:22"/>they are according to God's Appointment; yea, and then we may pray for God's Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon them: But you can neither pray for a Bleſſing upon theſe Laws, that are now in Being, nor expect a Bleſſing upon them; but that at the ſame time, you muſt ſin againſt God: Becauſe the Laws in themſelves are Eſſentially ſinful, therefore, we can no more pray for them, ſo as to be heard and accepted with God, than the <hi>Jews</hi> could pray for a Bleſſing upon that Bloody Law of theirs, by which they Crucified our Saviour Chriſt, the Eternal Son of God, without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> I Exhort you all to return to your 19th Article, which ſaid Article alone, condemns all your violent Practices, and alſo your wicked Laws; and let all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Unite in Love, and in the fear of the Lord, and let every man live peaceably, and let us all be ſubject to the higher Powers; <hi>for the Powers that be are of God:</hi> And let every man be perſwaded in his own Mind; for every man muſt give an Account of himſelf to God: Let us ſtudy Peace with all men; let us deviſe liberal things, for by liberal things we ſhall ſtand; the Word of God ſaith it. Let us mind the Law and Light of Nature, which our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour Chriſt did Honour and Sanctifie, and gave Heavenly Sanction unto: <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.12. <hi>Therefore, all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ye would that Men ſhould do to you, do ye even ſo to them: For this is the Law and the Prophets. All things whatſoever:</hi> Here the Royal Command of the King of Heaven, is, <hi>All things whatſoever ye would that Men ſhould do unto you;</hi> and not in this or that thing, and not in the other, but in <hi>All things whatſoever.</hi> Our Saviour Chriſt bringeth it in Argumentatively, therefore, <hi>All things whatſoever:</hi> It is both Argumentatively, and Univerſally, and therefore, <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts</hi> muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded; for they are things that produceth great Miſchief to be done, againſt all ſorts of Diſſenters, ſuch as without any forcible Arguments, beſides what it carrieth in its own Bowels, I believe no Church-of-<hi>England</hi>-Man would be willing to have done unto him. Now, if you that are for the continuing the Teſt againſt the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> and other Diſſenters, would not that they ſhould get into the Government, and Exclude you, and make Laws againſt you, to keep you out of the Government; and not only ſo, but ruine you and your Families: Then why do you do ſo unjuſtly by them? For Chriſt ſaith, <hi>This is the Law and the Prophets;</hi> he you contented with your equal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of the Government, in common with other Free-born <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men, and fellow Subjects; for the Law of God is for Juſtice; and the Prophets of God are for Juſtice: For one of them hath ſaid, <hi>Do Juſtice, Love Mercy, and walk Humbly with the Lord thy God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> I Exhort all you, That were <hi>Teſt-makers,</hi> and <hi>Teſt-givers,</hi> and <hi>Teſt-takers,</hi> to have a care; and do not oppoſe the King's Majeſty in His Gracious Declaration, and fixed Reſolution, to Aboliſh and utterly Deſtroy both one, and all theſe Yokes and Snares from His People's Necks and Feet; and to make his People, a free and happy People: <hi>For if it be of God, it will ſtand: Ye cannot over throw it, least haply ye be found even to fight againſt God.</hi> His Majeſty does not act alone in this Matter; but he is Influenced by an Omnipotent Arm: I dare, with humble Submiſſion to God, ſay by theſe <hi>Penai Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> as the Prophet did of the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Jer. 37.10. Although His Majeſty had none but a Company of <hi>Wounded Men</hi> on his ſide; yet His Majeſty with them, ſhould Aboliſh, and for ever Deſtroy all theſe Snares and Snakes, that are apparently ſo; and make better Laws for the Security of our Chriſtian Liberty, in the Room of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly</hi> and <hi>Laſtly,</hi> I Exhort all you of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that have been at the Sacrament formerly or latterly, to Examine your ſelves, what you went to the Lord's Table for? Or, if you pleaſe, give me leave to ask you a few Queſtions: 1. <hi>What was
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50785:22"/>your Buſineſs at the Lord's Table?</hi> 2. Pray, <hi>What Condition did you go unto this Holy Ordinance in?</hi> 3. <hi>Who did you expect to meet with there?</hi> 4. And laſtly, <hi>What Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit did you receive, or expect to receive at this Holy Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> What Buſineſs had you at the Sacrament? Did you go there, for fear of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing the Parſon? Or, Did you go there, becauſe your Neighbours ſhould have a better Eſteem of you, that they ſhould think you are a good Chriſtian? Or, Did you go to ſatisfie the Laws of Men, that binds ye ſo to do? Or, Did you go there to quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie your ſelves to come into the Government? Or, Did you go there to ſatisfie and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et a Natural Conſcience? What was your End and Aim in going there, and partaking of that Sacred Ordinance? Was it in Obedience to Chriſt's Command? Pray, do you give the Anſwer unto God, and your own Conſciences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In what condition did you go unto the Lord's Table? Were you born of God? For this is the <hi>Children's Bread,</hi> and for none elſe. Or, Did you go and ruſh upon this Bleſſed Ordinance in your Sins? Were you Regenerated and born of God before e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you came there? For the ſame Graces that fits a Perſon for Eternal Salvation in Glory, fits him for a Right Worthy Receiving of this Holy Ordinance of the <hi>Lord's Supper;</hi> therefore thoſe do run a deſperate Hazzard, that do drive off Repentance, and the getting all other Graces of the Spirit, until they come to lye on their Death-bed; when pale Death looks them grimly in the Face, and is ready to launch them out into the Ocean of Eternity: And then to expect, that this Ordinance of the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> ſhall bring all theſe Graces along with it, to fit them for Heaven and Eternal Glory; whenas, they muſt have the ſame Graces to fit them for this Holy Ordinance, which is lodged in the Kingdom of Heaven below, as is to fit them for the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven above; this being no Converting Ordinance: For the Text in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29. tells us plainly, That <hi>he that Eateth and Drinketh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthily, Eateth and Drinketh Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to himſelf, not diſcerning the Lord's Body:</hi> Therefore, I beſeech ye all in the Spirit of Meekneſs, and in the fear of the Lord, that are of this Opinion, to conſider ſeriouſly of it; becauſe Conſideration is a good Hand-Maid unto Reformation; for this Ordinance does not bring one dram of Grace along with it unto any Soul, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch as have Grace in their Hearts before receiving this Ordinance: It is like the pouring of Water into a Pump, that ſtandeth in a Well that hath Water in it, to fetch the Water: But the giving this Ordinance to any Perſon that hath no Grace, is like the pouring of Water into a Pump, that ſtandeth in a Well, that hath no Water in it: It is as Water ſpilt upon the Ground, nay it is infinitely worſe. But then, did you ever feel the powerful Operation of the Holy Ghoſt, dart ſpiritual Light into your Souls, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you come to ſee that which you never ſee before, and feel that in your ſelves, which you never ſee nor felt before? Have your Souls been raiſed out of the Grave of Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief? Out of a carnal, corrupt, dead State, by the mighty Power of the Spirit? And has it infuled Spiritual Life into you? Hath that Almighty Power that raiſed a dead Saviour, raiſed thee that was a poor dead Sinner? Have you ever found and felt Sin to be an intollerable Burthen unto your Souls, ſo as you have apprehended your ſelves to be in a loſt and undone Condition? Have you ever been made ſenſible of the want of Chriſt, who calleth the <hi>Burthened, Weary, and Heavy laden Sinner unto him,</hi> for Eaſe and Relief? And has it made you forſake all your Sins and Luſts, and all other things that come in Competition with Chriſt, to follow him fully? Have you been throughly convinced, that nothing could Redeem you from Wrath and Hell, and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tone you to God, and Purchaſe Eternal Life and Salvation for you, but Chriſt; and that by and through his Righteouſneſs and Merits alone? Did you cry to God, and ſay, <hi>Lord give me Chriſt, or I die, and ſhall be Damned, and never enjoy God; nor have
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:50785:23"/>any Benefits by his Death, and Bleſſed All-ſufficient-Merits, and Copious Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi> Had you the Kingdom of God within ye, before you came into that, which you apprehend to be the Kingdom of God without ye; namely the Church? Did you know what you were to take it for, before you came to the Lord's Table? And Pray, What frame of Heart did you go to the Sacrament in? Were your Graces in a lively Exerciſe? Did all thoſe ſparkling Jewels that adorn the Soul of the Believer, ſhine forth in their Vigour and Luſtre; which is the Trimming that belongeth to the <hi>Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Garment?</hi> And did you ſee him whom your Soul loved, and longed for? And did you diſcern the Lord's Body by an Eye of Faith, through the Elements? And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him by a Hand of Faith, and feed upon him with the Mouth of Faith? Did you go to the Table of the Lord, even ſick of Love to Chriſt? And could nothing ſatisfie your Hungring Thirſty Soul, but Communion with Chriſt in that Ordinance? And did you Exerciſe ſaving Faith, and Spiritual Light and Knowledge, and godly Sorrow for your Sins, which was the Cauſe of Chriſt ſuffering and dying? And did you receive him with Praiſe and Thankſgiving, and with a Holy Vehement Deſire?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Who did you expect to meet withal at the Lord's Table? Did you expect to meet with a Crucified Saviour there, and to have Communion with him in that Bleſſed Ordinance? Or, Did you go only to meet with the Parſon, and others of your Neighbours there? Did you ſee him by an Eye of Faith, that ſhould be your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, and the beloved of your Soul? Or, Are you wholly ignorant, of what Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God in that Ordinance meaneth?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> What did you expect to receive at the Lord's Table? Did you expect to receive the Bread and Wine only, and to feed upon that? Or, Did you expect to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt, which is the ſpiritual Bread and Drink of your Souls, into your Hearts; and ſo to receive a freſh Pardon, ſealed unto you for all your Sins? Did you go away thence, with God's Broad Seal Impreſſed afreſh upon your Souls? And your Covenant-Intereſt with God, Ratified and Confirmed unto you in the Blood of the Lamb? And your Eternal Salvation made ſure unto you? But if on the contrary, you went to that Ordinance in a Carnal, Unconverted, Dead State; you came away with the Guilt of all your Sins faſter bound and ſealed up, than they were before you came there; and inſtead of diminiſhing and weakning your Sins, you went away with your Sins increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſtrengthened. Now, Pray Examine your ſelves; Do you know what theſe things meaneth? Or, Are you wholly ignorant of them, as old <hi>Nicodemus</hi> was, when our Bleſſed Saviour Preached unto him the Myſterious Doctrine of Regeneration; when he thought, <hi>he muſt Re-enter into his Mothers Womb, and be born again?</hi> Joh. 3.4. Are all theſe things Riddles and Fancies unto ye? Do you know nothing of this Matter? Are you a ſtranger to it? And are you wholly ignorant of it? If you are, I tell you plainly, that you are no fit Subjects of this Bleſſed Ordinance; but you did come unto it, and partake of it unworthily; therefore I will refer you, to the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>'s Cenſure in this Caſe; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. If you had not your Mind ſavingly Enlightned, nor your Will Renewed and Changed, nor your Affection Rectified and ſet upon right Objects, <hi>viz.</hi> upon God in Chriſt: And if you had not ſanctifying ſaving Faith fixt upon Chriſt, the only Mediator and Redeemer of Mankind; 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. And if you did not come with your Hearts broken for Sin, and from Sin, and behold a Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified Saviour, with all your Sins Crucified; not one ſpared or Indulged: And if you did not come there, with a New Spiritual Underſtanding, nor the whole Man ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied throughout, in Body, Soul and Spirit. But if you came to the Lord's Table, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of all this, and in all your Sins; then inſtead of receiving any Benefit by, or from this Ordinance, <hi>you do Eat and Drink Judgment, or Condemnation to your ſelves, not diſcerning the Lord's Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:50785:23"/>
            <p>But it may be ſome will be ſo bold and hardy, as to ſay, <hi>This is very ſevere, harſh Doctrine:</hi> Why, this is nothing but what I looked for and expected; for it is what car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Hypocrites, and proud Perſecuters do always judge of God's Holy Word, and Righteous Laws, and Pure Ordinances, Inſtitutions and Worſhip: They judge that to be too ſtrict, and his Holy People to be too preciſe. But if you will quarrel at the Severity and Strictneſs of this Doctrine, you muſt quarrel with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles and Prophets: Nay, let me tell ye, if you will quarrel with this Doctrine, you muſt diſpute the Cauſe with our Saviour Chriſt himſelf, if you dare. What dare not they do, that dare to Crucifie their Maker, that ſhould be their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer? For the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> delivered nothing of this ſevere, harſh Doctrine, but what he received firſt from the Lord, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23. There is his Miſſion; and the Prophets ſpake as they were inſpired by the Holy Ghoſt; 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. <hi>For the Prophecy came not in Old time by the Will of Man: But Holy Men of God ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> You do find fault with the Severity of God's Laws againſt Sinners; but you do not find fault with the Severity of your own Laws againſt his Saints and Servants, and againſt your ſelves alſo: For there the Severity of it will center at laſt; for you have Laws in being, which you are now contending for, to have continued with us, which are to force men to break and violate all theſe ſevere Laws of God, as you count them, and thereby to incur all the Penalties of them: And who is ſevereſt, the God of Mercy, or you that are Men of this Cruelty? There are very ſevere Laws made againſt any that ſhould even dare to Counterfeit the King's Broad-Seal, or to fix the Impreſs of it unto any thing, which they have not His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Command, and Authority for ſo doing; it is puniſhable with Death by the Law, for it is High Treaſon; or if they ſhould fix it to Blank Papers, whereby Enemies might write what they pleaſe, and ſo abuſe and betray the King's Authority: Why! This Ordinance of the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> is the Broad-Seal of Heaven, it belongeth to the <hi>King of Kings,</hi> and muſt not be affixed to, or impreſſed upon any thing, but what they have God's Authority for ſo doing. Now, for any Perſons to take this Sacred Broad-Seal of Heaven, and make it a common Seal; namely, to affix it to the civil State, to Seal Men Commiſſions and Warrants for Places and Offices, in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Civil, Military, and Eccleſiaſtical; this is to make this Bleſſed Ordinance a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Seal. 2. It is a making this Sacred Broad-Seal of Heaven a common Seal, when they Seal a Licence to ſell Ale with it by. And <hi>Thirdly</hi> and <hi>Laſtly,</hi> They make this Bleſſed Ordinance of the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> which is the Broad-Seal of Heaven, a common Seal, when at Feſtival Times, as <hi>Christmas</hi> and <hi>Eaſter,</hi> when whole Showles of poor ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Creatures comes to the <hi>Lord</hi>'s Table, that know not their Right-Hand from their Left, in ſpiritual Things; and have no ſaving Work of God wrought in their Souls, by the powerful Operation of his Holy Spirit; but are all it may be, as ignorant as the very Parſon that Exhibits it unto them: Theſe are all Blanks, ſo they impreſs the Broad-Seal of Heaven upon Multitudes of Blanks; ſo that the <hi>Evil One</hi> may come, and write what he pleaſes after them. O ſad deplorable Condition, for any poor Souls to be in! And although you count this Doctrine ſevere and harſh, yet no man can be ignorant of it; becauſe it is written in the Great Charter of Heaven, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>He that Eateth and Drinketh unworthily, Eateth and Drinketh Condemnation, or Judgment to himſelf.</hi> God hath threatned to execute ſevere Judgments and Puniſhments upon all Propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and Abuſers of this Holy Ordinance: And God hath Four Gracious Ends in threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning theſe Tranſgreſſions. 1. It is to Deter and and Affright Sinners, from violating theſe ſevere Laws, as they call them, that Perſons ſhould not be ignorant of them. 2. God threatens, becauſe that Sinners might repent, and prevent the Execution of thoſe ſevere Laws. 3. God threatens, becauſe he will leave the Sinner wholly without Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:50785:24"/>or Plea; <hi>Every Mouth ſhall be ſtop'd.</hi> And 4. and <hi>Laſtly,</hi> God threatens, becauſe the Glory of his Attribute of Juſtice ſhall appear to all the World, when he Executes his Threatning upon the Guilty Impenitent Sinner, <hi>every Mouth will be ſtop'd;</hi> and all ſhall juſtifie God, and ſay, <hi>Righteous art thou, O Lord, and Juſt and Holy in all thy Ways:</hi> Thus you ſee what a dangerous thing it is, for poor, ignorant, carnal, uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, dead Sinners, to ruſh upon this Ordinance Hand over Head, without due Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, of what they are going about to do.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Secondly,</hi> My Second and laſt Exhortation, and Counſel ſhall be, unto all ſober Proteſtants, both of Diſſenters and others, that are ſtill hankering after the <hi>Onions,</hi> and <hi>Garlick,</hi> and <hi>Fleſh-Pots</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that are yet ſtaying upon them that ſmote us.</p>
            <p>And my firſt Exhortation unto all you, ſhall be this, namely, Be not afraid to part with the very Cauſe, or preſent ſtate of Suffering, for fear of future Sufferings; for the Cauſe is worſe than the Effects of Suffering: For while the Cauſe is in being, the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects may ſoon be produced again: For to be afraid of future Suffering, is to remain under preſent Sin. What Sin, you will ſay? Why, Chriſt is ſtill Crucifying upon the Croſs of the Sacramental Teſt, and ever will be, until that Law be Aboliſhed and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed. O Sirs! I beſeech ye, do not deal by your Bleſſed Saviour, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Butler did by <hi>Joſeph,;</hi> when he had gotten his own Elargement, and was at Eaſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he ſoon forgot the Afflictions of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> whom he promiſed to remember, when he came before the King. O! Do not you deal ſo unkindly by our Saviour Chriſt, now you have gotten your Liberty, and are at Eaſe your ſelves: Do not forget that Chriſt our Bleſſed Jeſus is in Sufferings ſtill; he is ſtill upon the Croſs of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Teſt; for if you do, you may provoke God to bring you into greater Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, than ever you have been yet in, and that from the immediate Hand of God; for though the Lord <hi>B—s</hi> have diſcharged all their Artillery againſt ye, yet God may diſcharge his againſt ye; and you cannot ſhift nor ſhun that: as perhaps moſt of you of this Leven, formerly have done. In time of actual Perſecution and Sufferings, you could go to the Outward-Court-Worſhip one part of the Lord's Day, and to a private Meeting to Worſhip, at Night; which was grievous Hypocriſie, and down-right mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God, and a Halting between two Opinions: <hi>If the Lord be God, follow him; if</hi> Baal, <hi>then follow him.</hi> The Lord give Repentance unto all that were thus guilty; for now it is a ſpecial time for all men to be ſerious.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Study your preſent Duty, and do it, let it be what it will; follow God in the Footſteps of his Providence, and be not afraid to lay your Hand on the <hi>Cockatrice</hi> Den, to deſtroy it; namely, the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> for fear of an <hi>uncertain Snake in the Graſs:</hi> Let this legal Old Houſe, which the Plaiſter and Stones, and the very Timber of it is infected with this fretting Leproſie, be pulled down and utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; or elſe this Plague of Perſecution, which is the worſt of Plagues, will never be ſtop'd: Do not think of Preſerving this Stone, or that piece of Timber, but down with it all; raze the very Foundation of it, and build a better Houſe in the room of it: For the very End and Deſign of theſe Laws, was but to ſtrengthen the Hands of Evil doers: And ſhall any ſober man of any Perſwaſion, even dare to be for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of them? And ſhould conſequentially chooſe rather, that Chriſt the Son of God ſhould remain Crucified, and bleeding under them, than to part with them, for fear of the <hi>Snake in the Graſs:</hi> It is a ſign of but little Love to Chriſt; they love their own preſent Eaſe, and prefer that before the Sufferings of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Let not any Sober Man be afraid to come into the Government, nor let not them be Uneaſy that are in it, whom God by his Majeſty hath or ſhall call into it, becauſe they have not, nor cannot take the Sop of Qualification, which is a very great Sin in them that have thus Sinfully qualified themſelves; they that have not thus
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50785:24"/>Unworthily complyed, will have the moſt Peace and Comfort: Shall any man be afraid to do good, for fear of evil coming on it? For theſe Inſnaring Laws are againſt the Great Charter of Heaven, and therefore it is that Perſecuters are ſo much for them, and ſo ready to Obey them, and to Comply with them; and therefore good Men all along have refuſed to yield Obedience unto them, but have choſen rather to Suffer, and be Ruined by them, then Sinfully to Comply with them; becauſe that Wicked Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Men, and Good Men, are of two contrary Principles, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.27. <hi>An <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt man is an Abomination to the Juſt: And he that is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright in the way, is an Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the Wicked.</hi> O my Beloved! As you do value the Honour and Glory of God, and his Majeſty's Kindneſs, and the Peace and Tranquility of your Country, and the Good of your Poſterity, come into the Government, and put your Hand to this Plow of God, and do not look back, but follow God in his Footſteps of Providence; hear what that Goſpel Prophet ſaith, which ſeems to be very appoſite to this purpoſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.20. <hi>Come my People, enter thou into thy Chambers, and ſhut thy Doors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thee, hide thy ſelf, as it were, for a little moment, until the Indignation be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt,</hi> I take this to be the ſame with the Great Voice that came from Heaven, which brought us our <hi>Chriſtian Liberty;</hi> that ſaid, <hi>Come up hither, Rev.</hi> 11.12. That is, <hi>Come into your Chambers, Meet publickly, for all the Glorious Attributes of God are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged for your Safety, which are the Chambers of Heaven:</hi> Well, but what is theſe Doors, and the ſhutting of that? Why, I humbly conceive theſe Doors to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which expoſeth us to danger while it ſtands open; theſe Doors that are open up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, may be meant of the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts;</hi> which all the Perſecuting Thieves and Robbers, who are the Enemies of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> do always enter in at, and Rob, and Rape, and Spoil all that are not of their Party, that their Law or Luſts can reach: Therefore as God by his Gracious Majeſty's Declaration, hath called ye up into Heaven, into your Chambers, ſo God by his Majeſty, is now further calling upon ye to ſhut the Doors about ye, to keep out the Thieves and Robbers, that they may not come in to Rob and Spoil ye, for until that be done, you are not ſafe; neither can you, for though we have this <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> Bleſſed be God for it, yet the Doors ſtand open upon us, and the Thieves may come in again.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Secondly,</hi> What is this making faſt of theſe Doors round about us? Why, here is two things to be done, I humbly conceive.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is, You muſt deſtroy and take away all the Keys, or rather Legal Pick-Locks, which theſe Legal Thieves have; with which they can open your Doors at their pleaſure, and come in and Rob you of your Subſtance, and of your <hi>Chriſtian Liberty;</hi> Ay, and they Robbed ſome Men of their Conſciences alſo: And theſe Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Pick-Locks that let them in, was the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Secondly, You muſt make faſt theſe Doors of <hi>Christian Liberty,</hi> by making Juſt and Righteous Legal Locks, and Keys, and Bolts, and Bars unto them; even as his Majeſties moſt Generous Gracious Unſhaken Reſolution is for having this <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> made into a perpetual <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> that may be more Unalterable then thoſe Laws of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> were: And this is to ſhut the Doors round about us, to ſecure our <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> unto us. And pray Obſerve, how well the Text and his Majeſty's Reſolutions for theſe Doors being ſhut doth agree, as well as in many other things which I could Obſerve concerning this <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> which he hath given us, or reſtored unto us out of the Hands of them that had Uſurped it, and Detained it from us; and that is this, <hi>Enter thou into THY Chambers:</hi> Which notes unto us, that it is the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Right, as his Gracious Majeſty hath well Obſerved, That <hi>Conſcience</hi> ought not to be Reſtrained in meer Matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> which is the ſame thing in effect. Whence we may Obſerve, from the Word of God, and from the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:50785:25"/>the Kings Declaration, That <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> is a Man's own property. My Beloved, be not afraid to come into the Government upon this Topic, and act Couragiouſly with his Majeſty, for Eſtabliſhing of this our <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> which you ſee is our own property; I do not doubt, but his Majeſty is Acted by the Divine Over-Ruling Hand, which Directs him to take ſuch juſt Methods, as never any of his Predeceſſours did in this nature; he is acted by a new Rule, given him down from Heaven; he Treads in an Uncouth Path, that never was Troden before by any Prince of the World, and therefore the Glory of the Wiſdom of God, the Efficient firſt moving Cauſe, does ſhine forth the more Splendidly and Conſpicuous; even him, <hi>by whom Kings Reign, and Princes Decree Juſtice; in whoſe Hand the King's Heart is; and as the Rivers of Waters, he turneth it whereſoever he will.</hi> And what a brave Confeſſion did <hi>Darius</hi> make of the Soveraignty of God, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.26, 27. <hi>I make a Decree, that in every Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my Kingdom, men tremble and fear before the God of</hi> Daniel. Why, what was the matter? Why, their <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts</hi> had caſt <hi>Daniel</hi> into the Lyons Den, fore againſt the Kings Will; his Nobles had got his Royal Aſſent unto it, under a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Pretence of Loyalty to the King; which was only to make a Snare to catch <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> in; for they had no way to Inſnare him, but in the matters of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, Dan.</hi> 6.3, 4, 5, 6, 7. Hence we way Obſerve, that pretended Loyalty has been a Cloak of Old to Hypocriſie; they got a Law made, <hi>viz. That if any Perſon ſhould put a Petition to any God or Man for thirty days, ſave of thee, O King, he ſhall be caſt into the Lyons Den.</hi> They knew this would do <hi>Daniel</hi>'s buſineſs for him; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the beſt Subject or Slave that the King had, as by their own Confeſſion. <hi>V.</hi> 5. <hi>Then ſaid theſe men, We ſhall not find any Occaſion againſt this</hi> Daniel, <hi>except we find it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him concerning the Law of his God.</hi> Hence we may obſerve by the way, that Men of Principles has been very faithful to Princes, when they have impoſed any Truſt in them; as <hi>Joſeph</hi> to <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> and <hi>Obadiah,</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> and theſe Three Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies in <hi>Daniel;</hi> and <hi>Mordecai,</hi> who ſaved King <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> Life, though all of them <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from the National Worſhip, but this by the by.</p>
            <p>But to return to <hi>Daniel</hi> in particular, They had nothing againſt him to faſten any Snare upon him, <hi>but for praying to his God.</hi> And for that he was caſt into the Lyons Den; but God ſhut the Mouths of the Lyons, ſo that they did not hurt him. But the King cauſed the Executioners of that Law to be <hi>caſt into the Lyons Dens themſelves,</hi> and then the Lyons Mouths was opened, and they Devoured them, <hi>Verſe</hi> 24. So that it is no new thing for Perſecuters to be taken in their own Snares: But to return to the Kings Confeſſion of the Deity, for ſays he, <hi>He is the Living God, and ſtedfaſt for ever, and his Kingdom that which ſhall not be deſtroyed; and his Dominion ſhall be even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end; he Delivereth and Reſcueth; and he worketh Signs and Wonders in Heaven, and in Earth; who hath Delivered</hi> Daniel <hi>from the power of the Lyons.</hi> And yet this King was not of <hi>Daniels</hi> Religion, notwithſtanding all his Love and Kindneſs unto him, but he was acted by the Divine Influence of Heaven; his Heart was in God's Hand, as all Kings Hearts are, and that was the reaſon on it. O Sirs! Do not think that theſe great Providences and Diſpenſations cometh out of the Duſt, or by Luck or Chance, or men's Projects: Theſe great things that we have ſeen, do not come of themſelves; neither do they come in vain, or to little purpoſe; but as they are Influenced by the Almighty Hand of God, who hath the Reins of all Power and Government his own Hand, and turneth them this way or that way, or which way ſoever he pleaſeth, for the fulfilling of his Predeterminate Counſels and Glorious Deſigns in the World, and for the bringing forth of his Eternal Decrees, which the Womb of Providence is now Traveling with, and will bring forth; and our preſent Providences are as ſo many Bleſſed <hi>Harbingers</hi> and fore-runners of Glorious things, that are yet to be accompliſhed in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50785:25"/>this latter Age of the World, that is even at the Door, both at home and abroad; look for it, and expect it, and alſo prepare for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Let us all be of a forgiving Diſpoſition, and frame of Heart: Let us be ready and willing to forgive our Enemies. But yet notwithſtanding, we muſt do it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rule and Way which our Saviour Chriſt himſelf hath preſcribed in his holy Word, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.21, 22. <hi>Then came</hi> Peter <hi>to him and ſaid, Lord, how oft ſhall my Brother Sin againſt me, and I forgive him? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil ſeven times? Jeſus ſaith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, I ſay not unto thee, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil ſeven times: But until ſeventy times ſeven.</hi> Here is the Duty; but in <hi>Luke</hi> 17.3, 4. there our Saviour hath laid down the manner and conditions on which it muſt be done, therefore pray mind it narrowly—<hi>Take heed to your ſelves, if thy Brother Treſpaſs againſt thee, Rebuke him; and if he Repent, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give him; and if he Treſpaſs againſt thee ſeven times in a day, and ſeven times in a day return unto thee, ſaying, I Repent; thou ſhalt forgive him.</hi> Here you ſee is the Duty, and on what Conditions this great piece of <hi>Chriſtian Duty</hi> muſt be performed in a right Goſpel manner; even to an Offending Brother. But ſome will ſay, That we ought to forgive our Perſecuting Enemies; which is true, I am clearly for it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they come within the Verge of Chriſt's Command. But I do not find that we ought to forgive them, if they do not Repent, and Confeſs, and make Reſtitution for the Wrongs and Injuries they have done us. It is true, <hi>We are to Love our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and Bleſs them that Curſe us, and to do good to them that Hate us, and to pray for them which Deſpightfully <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe us, and Perſecute us,</hi> Mat. 5.44. We muſt not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain any Perſonal Prejudice againſt them, we muſt ſo Forgive them in our Hearts: But ſome pretend to forgive our Perſecuting Enemies, though we do not ſee at all, that they do Repent and Turn to us by asking of Forgiveneſs of us, though they have Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed many of us of our Goods, and Abuſed us otherwiſe; but I can find no Warrant at all in Scripture for ſo doing; but this is to make the Door of Forgiveneſs wider then the Wiſdom of God hath made it: Nay, it is againſt the very Tenour of the Goſpel, for there muſt be a turning to them whom they have Offended, and an acknowledging their Fault, and a Humbling themſelves for it, and a making all the Satisfaction they are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, to the party wronged, which is but Juſt; for Mercy and Juſtice are joyned together by God, and let no man part them aſunder; God never deſtroys his Juſtice, by extending his Mercy: I do not find that Perſecuters have a priviledge above any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſons; nay, then a Child of God himſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> an Offending Brother, for there muſt be a Reſtitution, or elſe you overthrow the Scriptures, <hi>Job</hi> 20.15, 18. Pray look into the ground-work and plat-form of Repentance, and there you ſhall ſee that one great part of Repentance is clearing, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11. as a man clears his Stomach, when he Vomits up ſomething which lay heavy and ponderous upon it, by which means he is eaſed; ſo here there muſt be Reſtitution, or there can be no true Repentance; as you may ſee in that Inſtance of <hi>Zaccheus, Luke</hi> 19.8. who had been a great Extortioner, he was for Reſtitution. I am clearly for forgiving our Perſecuting Enemies in Gods way; but yet I do not think it is my Duty, if a Thief has Robbed me, and is carrying away my Goods, to run after him and cry, <hi>I pardon you Sir:</hi> When he neither regard what I ſay unto him, nor returns me my Goods: I think it is rather my Duty to Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend him, and bring him to Juſtice, then to follow him with a Pardon: Which lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is like unto conſenting to a Thief, or at leaſt to encourage him in his ſinful courſe of Life, which is forbidden in Scripture—<hi>When thou ſeeſt a Thief, conſent thou not:</hi> or ſuppoſing it to be a Company of Legal Religious Thieves, ſuch as are in <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.14. <hi>Alſo the Robbers of thy People ſhall Exalt themſelves to Eſtabliſh the Viſion, but they ſhall fall.</hi> Theſe are the worſt of Thieves, that Rob, as they pretend, <hi>for Gods ſake:</hi> Now is it a reaſonable thing, that we ſhould run after theſe men that have done until
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:50785:26"/>this Milchief and Spoil, and pray them to accept of Pardon from us, without their firſt ſeeking and turning unto us by Repentance, and acknowledging their Crime, and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they have taken from us again, according to their Subſtance or Ability, as God hath Ordained? O no; for it is contrary to Scripture.</p>
            <p>But ſome People are apt to ſay, <hi>That this bringing the Perſecuters before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, looks like Revenge; and we ought rather to forgive them.</hi> But one thing I mind, It is thoſe aſſert this, that have not ſuffered much by them themſelves; ſuch as perhaps could tell how to ſhift their Tides, that are ſo Merciful and Wiſe above what is Written; but I am apt to ſuſpect theſe kind of Peoples new faſhioned Clemency, that pretend to ſo much Mercy above their Neighbours in this caſe; I fear this Charity is not grounded upon a ſolid Foundation, I doubt we ſhall find but a ſandy Foundation at bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom; I could find in my Heart to try whether it be ſo or no, becauſe it doth not look well. <hi>To the Law, and to the Teſtimony: If they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe they have no Light them,</hi> Iſa. 8.20.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, you that are ſo full of Charity, that are for forgiving thoſe Wicked Perſecuting Spoiling Thieves, before they ask ye, or make any reſtitution; when God hath ſaid, <hi>That there muſt be a Reſtitution of all things;</hi> which is to overthrow that Word of God by not having it fulfilled, and ſo tacitly to make God a Lyar, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.20.21. <hi>Job</hi> 20.15, 18. Now let us Examine whether this proceeds from pure Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Clemency, or whether it does not proceed from Slaviſh Fears and Cowardly Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. Firſt, If it proceeds from pure Lenity, then it muſt be Univerſal, and extended to all that cometh within that Circle of Mercy and Clemency; and eſpecially in things that more immediately concerns a mans own ſelf, than this, and is more at a mans own diſpoſal, than theſe things are. Firſt, If you be a Uſurer, or if you be a Land-Lord, or a Tradeſman, that are ſo full of this new faſhioned Charity; why now, if you be in good Earneſt, let the Uſurer go home, and take all his Bonds and Cancel them, and forgive them both Principal and Intereſt; and let the Land-Lord forgive all his Tenants; and let the Tradeſman Croſs out all his Debtors out of his Book, and forgive them all, and then I will believe you are in good earneſt; for it is more in your power to do ſo, then to forgive your Enemies without Satisfaction, according to Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, although it was you your ſelves that they had Robbed and Plundered: Do you forgive that which is your own to forgive, firſt, Before you do forgive that which is Gods or another Mans; or elſe I will never believe that you are in good Earneſt, but that it is rather the Product of Slaviſh Fears, and of a Carnal Cowardly frame of Heart; for God is more concerned in all the Wrongs and Injuries which is done to his People on the Account of Religion and Conſcience, then his People themſelves are; for as they that Perſecute them, do fight againſt God, and Perſecute Chriſt, ſo they that do Rob them, do alſo Rob God himſelf; ſo that you have more power to give away, or to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them Honeſt Debtors of yours, that are Indebted unto you upon the Account of Trade, then you have to forgive the Perſecuting Robbers and Spoilers, becauſe all the damage that is done to Gods People, God takes it as done to himſelf, <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.8. <hi>For thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, After the Glory, hath he ſent me unto the Nations which ſpoiled you; for he that toucheth you, toucheth the Apple of his Eye.</hi> My Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, now I have tryed you by the Word of God, do you try your ſelves, for theſe be trying times: I hope you do not count it Revenge, when you ſeek for your own, what a Man juſtly oweth you, although you ſhould be forc'd to make uſe of the Law to get it.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, In the fifth place, my Advice and Counſel to all you that are Sober Honeſt Men, is thus, That you would not Fear, Truſt, nor hearken to the Threats nor Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of theſe your Perſecuting Enemies. Do not ſay a Confederacy with them, let them
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:50785:26"/>ſpeak you never ſo fair or foul; and remember it is bad following the Counſel and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of an Enemy; but when they threaten, ſay with good <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> when he was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the like Circumſtance with us, <hi>Neh.</hi> 6.11. <hi>And I ſaid, Should ſuch a Man as I flee? And who is there, as being as I am, would go into the Temple to ſave his Life? I will not go in,</hi> He would not give way in the leaſt Degree to Unbelief and Slaviſh Fears: Brethren, let us all do ſo too, for <hi>Nehemiah</hi> had God and the King on his ſide, and ſo have we; And when they cog and flatter ye, then hearken to what is ſaid in <hi>Jer</hi> 12.6. <hi>For even thy Brethren, and the Houſe of thy Father, even they have dealt trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly with thee; yea, they have called a multitude after thee: Believe them not, though they ſpeak fair Words unto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly and Laſtly, My laſt Advice and Counſel unto you all, ſhall be this, <hi>Cast all your Care upon God, for he hath promiſed to take Care of you;</hi> God is never wanting on his part to them that put their truſt in him; God hath made it our Duty to caſt our Care upon him; and he hath made it his own Work and Buſineſs to take Care of us, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.22. But we are very apt and prone to take Gods Work out of his All-ſufficient Hand, and to be Peſtering our ſelves with Anxious Cares, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the very Vital Comforts of a Life of Faith, by Slaviſh Fears and Jealouſies; for the Counſel of the Lord, that ſhall ſtand, and cannot be altered by all the Powers in the World; and God is never at a loſs in his Work, nor out of his way in his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; <hi>the Lord hath his way in the Whirl-wind, and in the Storm, and the Clouds are the Duſt of his Feet,</hi> Nahum. 1.3. O truſt in the Lord! For in the Lord <hi>Jehovah</hi> is everlaſting ſtrength! Make God your Rock and Refuge, put your truſt in him alone, and Bleſs and Praiſe God for putting it into his Majeſty's Heart, to give and grant unto us this <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> and make a Sanctified improvement of it, for Gods Glory, and our own Souls Good; and be thankful to his Majeſty, and ſhew it by your endeavouring what in you lies, to contribute to the Eſtabliſhing and Fixing of it into a firm <hi>Magna Charta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you have ſeen, That this <hi>Sacramental Teſt</hi> hath had a fair Tryal by the plain Written Word of God, it has been weighed in the Ballance of the Sanctuary, and it is found lighter then Vanity; and it has been tryed by the Law of the Land, and that has found it Guilty of being Repugnant to the Law of God: And alſo it has been tryed by the 19th Article of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and that condemus it alſo; which ſaith, That the <hi>Sacranents</hi> muſt be duly miniſtred, and that only to a Congregation of <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Men</hi> in a Religious way and manner. And this <hi>Teſt</hi> you ſee is Arraigned, Caſt and Condemned by them all, and wants only a good Parliament to do Execution upon it, and make better Security in the room of theſe Sinful <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> which I Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly leave to the Great God, the Soveraign Majeſty of Heaven and Earth, to direct his Majeſty and the great Council of the Land, when he ſhall ſee it convenient to call and convene them together; and alſo to all Sober People, to be Careful and Wiſe in choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their Repreſentatives, to chooſe Sober, Wiſe, Diſcreet Men, of Honeſt Principles, and good Eſtates, that we may be freed from the Dreadful Spiritual Plagues and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which the Nation lieth under, and is Ingulfed into, and the dreadful Wrath of God, that hangeth over our Heads: God of his Mercy Awaken <hi>England</hi> to Repent before it be too late. I ſhall Conclude with theſe two Scriptures, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour all Men. Love the Brotherhood. Fear God. Honour the King.</hi> The other ſhall be with the Wiſe mans Concluſion of the Book of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> 12.13. <hi>Let us hear the Concluſion of the whole matter: Fear God, and keep his Commandments, for this is the whole Duty of Man; for God ſhall bring every work into Judgment, with every Secret thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evil.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:50785:27"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>BUT ſome will Object and ſay, <hi>Why ſhould ſuch Illiterate, Mean, Contemptible Perſons, meddle with ſuch Great and Publick Affairs as theſe are?</hi> Such things as theſe, are fit for none but the Learned Rabbies; ſuch as have long Heads, and well-furniſhed with a ſuitable ſtock of Brains, to undertake ſuch things as theſe are? It is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for ſuch as you, to meddle with your own private Affairs, than to meddle with Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of State. To this I ſhall Anſwer, and give you my Reaſons for this my Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in Eleven Particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, my firſt Reaſon is from that Holy Text, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26, 27, 28, 29. <hi>For you ſee your Calling, Brethren, how that not many Wiſe Men after the Fleſh, not many Mighty, not many Noble are called: But God hath choſen the Fooliſh things of the World, to confound the Wiſe; and God hath choſe the weak things of the World, to confound the things that are Mighty; and baſe things of the World, and things which are Deſpiſed, hath God choſen: Yea, and things which are not, to bring to nought things that are.</hi> And the Holy Ghoſt gives the Reaſon of this his Sovereign way of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, <hi>viz. That no Fleſh ſhould Glory in his Preſence.</hi> Now it is no where ſaid in Scripture, Not many Unlearned, not many Poor, Mean, Deſpicable Perſons, nor weak, that are nothing in the Eye and Eſteem of the World, that God hath not choſen: But it is ſaid, <hi>God hath Choſen the Poor in this World, Rich in Faith:</hi> Our Saviour Chriſt did not go to the Univerſities to pick and cull out Scholars, to make Apoſtles on, but he went to the <hi>Fiſher-Boats</hi> and choſe poor <hi>Fiſher-Men,</hi> and made them Fiſhers of Men. Therefore, I will challenge all the Objectors againſt this my Proceeding, to ſhew me in all the whole Book of God, from <hi>Geneſis</hi> to <hi>Revelations,</hi> where there is any one pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Promiſe made to the humane learned Men above their Fellows; not that I deſpiſe Learning, it is good in its place; but the over-valuing of it, has broached almoſt all the Errors and Hereſies that are in the World: The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, in 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.19, 20. <hi>Quench not the Spirit: Deſpiſe not Prophecying.</hi> And 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.30, 31. <hi>If any thing be revealed to another that ſitteth by, let the firſt hold his Peace: For ye may all Propheſie one by one, that all may learn, and all may be comforted.</hi> How few do ever mind theſe Scriptures? They are commonly neglected, and men's Gifts and Parts deſpiſed at this day, and that by the learned too: For, when do the People of God all <hi>Propheſie one by one?</hi> No forſooth, none but the Learned muſt do that, and if any one do attempt any ſuch thing, why, preſently there is Buckets of ſcornful Water thrown upon it, to quench the Spirit; and the Gift is deſpiſed, and ſo the Spirit is quenched; Propheſying is deſpiſed; for many will ſay, <hi>What Call have you to this or that, either to Speaking or Writing?</hi> Though it is ſaid, <hi>Many ſhall run to and fro, and Knowledge ſhall be increaſed;</hi> and in <hi>Amos</hi> 3, 8. They deal by the unlearned, as <hi>David</hi>'s Brethren dealt by him, when he left his Fathers Sheep to go and fight <hi>Goliah;</hi> though <hi>David</hi> was but a little man to fight with that great Giant, yet he had a great Heart, and was full of ſpiritual Mettle and holy Courage, becauſe he had the great God on his ſide. Pray mark the Carriage and Behaviour of his Elder Brother towards him, in a ſcornful, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing, contemptible way and manner; but yet that did not daunt him at all: 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.26, 27, 28, 29. <hi>And</hi> David <hi>ſpake to the Men that ſtood by him, ſaying, What ſhall be done to the Man that killeth this</hi> Philiſtine, <hi>and taketh away the Reproach of</hi> Iſrael? <hi>For who is this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſed</hi> Philiſtine, <hi>that he ſhould defie the Armies of the living God? And the People anſwered him after this manner, ſaying, So ſhall it be done
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50785:27"/>to the Man that killeth him. And</hi> Eliab <hi>his Eldest, Brother heard when he ſpake unto the Men, and</hi> Eliabs <hi>Anger was kindled againſt</hi> David, <hi>and he ſaid, Why cameſt thou down hither? And with whom haſt thou left thoſe few Sheep in the Wilderneſs? I know thy Pride, and the Naughtineſs of thy Heart.</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, <hi>What haſt thou to do to meddle with State-matters? Thou little deſpicable Shepherd, that art not worthy to be truſted with many Sheep; Why doſt thou neglect thy Calling? Be diligent in thy Calling.</hi> And he judged his Brothers Heart, <hi>Thou doſt it out of Pride and Auſtentation of Spirit, and in hopes to make thy ſelf great;</hi> He could ſee as far into <hi>David's</hi> Heart then, as ſome can into mine now: But pray mind <hi>David</hi>'s Anſwer then, and that ſhall ſerve for mine now; <hi>And David ſaid, What have I done? Is there not a Cauſe?</hi> Whence you may obſerve, That God's Cauſe was <hi>David</hi>'s Call, and ſo it is mine: His Brother thought it was a very unlikely thing, that ever ſuch a pititiful deſpicable Shepherd as he was, with his ſtaff in his Hand, and his Shepherds bag by his Side, with only five Stones in it, ſhould ever have ſlain Great <hi>Goliah,</hi> while his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and all the Great Men, and Valiant accompliſhed Souldiers, with the whole Hoſt of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſtood by and look'd on: It was a very unlikely thing that ſuch a Stripling as he was, ſhould conquer and kill that mighty Giant. But what is there too hard for the great God to do, by any means or Inſtrument he pleaſeth to make uſe of? Therefore let all the Honour and Glory, be aſcribed unto God, and not unto Inſtruments and Means.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> My greateſt Reaſon of all, for this my proceeding in this way and manner, is, Becauſe my great Lord and Maſter hangs upon the Croſs of the Sacramental Teſt, Vertually, and Myſtically, a Crucifying by the Penal Laws that are yet in being, and will do, until it be Aboliſhed; for though His Majeſty has done what in him lyeth to take him down, by which means, there is a Ceſſation of the Effects of it, with a reſpect to the Sufferings of his People; yet the Cauſe, which is worſe than the Effect, remains ſtill; and there are ſome Perſons that refuſe to put their Hands to help to take him down from this Croſs; though God in his Providence, calleth upon us all now ſo to do: But let ſuch Perſons have a care, becauſe God is no Reſpecter of Perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> My Third Reaſon for this my Proceeding is this; <hi>viz.</hi> Becauſe Truth was Treaſon with the Perſecuters about four or five years ago; for if a man ſhould but have ſaid, That Conſcience ought not to be reſtrained in meer Matters of Religion, as His Majeſty in His Gracious Declaration has done, the Lord reward him for it: He would have been ſeverely dealt withal, and counted a Rebel and an Enemy to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and dealt withal as ſuch. For I knew a Friend of mine that was a Conſtable, that was complained againſt, becauſe he would not help to plunder his honeſt Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; and them that were then Juſtices, did wheedle him in to tell them, what his Reaſon was for not obeying their Warrant; whereupon he innocently (not thinking of the Snare that they had laid for him, by ſpeaking fair Words unto him) told them plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the Reaſon was, becauſe it was contrary to the Law of Jeſus Chriſt; and for this the honeſt Conſtable was ſent to Priſon, and fined a hundred Pounds, and paid it every Groat, beſides the loſs of his time, and the comfort of his Family, and Priſon Expences and Fees, which was a very hard Caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Another Reaſon for this my proceeding, is this, <hi>viz.</hi> Becauſe there was never a better Opportunity to bear a Teſtimony againſt that Antichriſtian Spirit of Perſecution, then there is now, having ſo good a Text for it from His Gracious Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty; by whom God hath born ſuch a clear Teſtimony againſt it from Heaven to all the World, in which he hath graciouſly, and conſequentially told us, <hi>That Conſcience ought not to be Reſtrained nor Oppreſſed by theſe Crucifying Oppreſſing Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:50785:28"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> My fifth Reaſon is, becauſe I bleſs God, I am not afraid to do good, for fear of evil coming of it; which is to continue in Sin that Grace may abound.</p>
            <p>Again, A ſixth Reaſon for this my Proceeding is, becauſe I am a Member of the Body Politick of the Nation; I am an <hi>Engliſh</hi>-man born, and therefore I ought to be uſeful to the ſaid Body; for what is a Member good for, that is not helpful to the Body? It is as if it were no Member.</p>
            <p>Again, My ſeventh Reaſon is, becauſe I find many Men of a <hi>Gallio</hi>-like Spirit; they care not for theſe things: A Spirit of Neutrality and Indifferency hath ſeized upon them; they are neither hot nor cold, they are Trimmers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> My eighth Reaſon for this my Proceeding is, becauſe I am bound in Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude towards God, for the Honour and Glory of God: And alſo, in point of Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to His Majeſty, into whoſe Heart God has been Graciouſly pleaſed to put it, to give and grant unto us this Glorious Liberty; and for the good of Souls, which is the beſt Service that I am capable to do in the Nation, and in my Generation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly,</hi> The Reaſon of this my Proceeding is, becauſe I will do my perſecuting Enemies all the good I can, while I live, in Obedience to God's Command, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44. <hi>But I ſay unto you, Love your Enemies, Bleſs them that Curſe you, do Good to them that hate you, and Pray for them which deſpitefully uſe you, and Perſecute you.</hi> But it may be you do not think that I have done you any good, in adviſing you to fall in with His Majeſty, to contribute to the compleating of this our Chriſtian Liberty; why then it is not ſo much to be wondred at, that the <hi>Jews</hi> would have put the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> to Death, for adviſing them to fall to the King of <hi>Babilon, Jer.</hi> 38.3, 4, 6, 17, 18. who was a great Idolater, and was the great Maſter of all Oppreſſing <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts;</hi> he was a Forreigner too; which was to go out of Liberty into Captivity, and to go out of their own Native Countrey alſo; I ſay, they had a far better Plea againſt him, to all outward Appearance, than any ſort of Men can have now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me; for I adviſe ye to go <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T</hi> of <hi>Captivity</hi> from all theſe <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> (which is as bad Captivity as that of <hi>Babilon</hi>) and to go into <hi>Chriſtian Liberty;</hi> into a firm <hi>Magna Charta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tenthly,</hi> My Tenth Reaſon for this my Proceeding is, Becauſe God hath given me a Wiſe and Six Children, and I would not willingly leave them with theſe Yokes about their Necks, and Shackles about their Legs, that we are all in Bondage too, if I can help it; for by the Laws that are now in being, they are Obliged to Receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper, at Sixteen Years of Age, whether they have true Grace or no Grace: Maturity of Years is made the ground of Communion with Chriſt, by this Law, and not True Sanctifying Saving Grace in the Heart, according to the word of God. So that theſe Poor Souls, according to this Law, are Tacitly and Conſequenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally bound to Eat and Drink their own Damnation, and to Crucifie to themſelves the Son of God afreſh, and put him to an open Shame betimes, even in their Youth. So that inſtead of Examining themſelves, to ſee whether they have true Grace to qualifie them for this Holy Ordinance: They muſt Examine themſelves to ſee how old they are, whether they be Sixteen Years Old; but theſe are ſuch Iron Yokes and Intolerable Burdens, that we nor our Children are able to bear. And therefore if my poor Mire will contribute any Service to his Gracious Majeſty to deſtroy them, I ſhall offer it willingly, when he has been pleaſed under God to offer it upon ſuch generous frank terms; and to have it ſecured unto us upon ſuch laſting Foundations: I believe if the Families of the Nation were divided into a Hundred Parts at leaſt, there would not be the Hundredth Family that had as many or more Children then I have, which I value more then the Riches and Honour of the World, for the former makes themſelves wings and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:50785:28"/>fly away; and the latter will be laid in the duſt: And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that provideth not for his Family, is worſe than an Infidel:</hi> And I think no better Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion can be made for our Children, than to leave them this Chriſtian Liberty well ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto them, planted in Peace and Tranquillity, which his Majeſty, the Father of the whole Family, namely, the whole Nation under God, is endeavouring to ſettle upon all his Children, which are his Subjects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eleventhly</hi> and laſtly, My reaſon for this my proceeding is this, <hi>viz.</hi> Becauſe I came of a very Ancient Family; for <hi>Adam</hi> was my great Grandfather, and <hi>Job</hi> and I had one Mother, and his Siſters are mine: <hi>Job</hi> 17.13, 14. <hi>The Grave is mine houſe; I have ſaid to Corruption, Thou art my Father; to the Worm, Thou art my Mother and my Siſter.</hi> And is not this an Ancient Family, think ye, to value my ſelf upon? And therefore why ſhould any body carp ſo much at the Meanneſs of this Author? And I pray, who is of an Ancienter Family than this is? Who is? Why the Perſecuter is as ancient, if not ancienter; for fallen Angels was before fallen Man: Pray, what Family is he of? Why our Saviour tells us, <hi>John</hi> 8. That <hi>they are of their Father the Devil, and the Luſts of their Father they will do.</hi> And this makes his perſecuting Children ſo full of Lyes, as they are at this time. Their Father ſtirs them up, and inſtigates them unto it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſeeth his Kingdom of Darkneſs going to be deſtroyed, and himſelf to be chain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: <hi>God will ſweep away the Refuge of Lyes,</hi> Iſai. 28.15, 17. <hi>Becauſe ye have ſaid, We have made a Covenant with Death, and with Hell are we at Agreement: When the overflowing ſcourge ſhall paſs through, it ſhall not come unto us; for we have made Lyes our Refuge, and under falſhood have we hid our ſelves: Judgment alſo will I lay to the Line, and Righteouſneſs to the Plummet; and the hail ſhall ſweep away the Refuge if Lyes, and the Waters ſhall overflow the hiding-place, and your Covenant with Death ſhall be diſanulled, and your Agreement with Hell ſhall not ſtand; when the overflowing Scourge ſhall paſs through, then you ſhall be trodden down by it.</hi> Now when the Penal Laws and Teſts ſhall be utterly deſtroyed, and the Refuge of Lyes all ſwept away; then as the Perſecuter will be left without an opportunity to perſecute, ſo will all ſorts of Perſons be left without any occaſion in the leaſt to Plot: For what does make any Man Plot, but the want of ſomething which is his Right, which he hath no hopes of coming at any other way, or by uſing any other means? Withdraw but the Fuel of Perſecution and Oppreſſion, and the Fire of Plotting and Rebellion will go out: Why, when every Man hath his Rights and Priviledges, Spiritual and Temporal, there will be no room left for Plotting: and if any one Party ſhould attempt to infringe any other ſingle Party of their Liberty; ſuch muſt make themſelves the common Enemy of all the reſt of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And what can any one ſingle Party do, againſt all the reſt of the Nation, that will then be united as one Man, and will value their Chriſtian Liberty above their Lives? Such preſumption would pull an old Houſe about their Ears; the Law of Nature would then be made uſe of, if they had no other Relief to have recourſe unto: But there is more in all theſe Fears and Jealouſies of the Perſecuters, than that of <hi>Popery,</hi> as they pretend; but I would adviſe them to be quiet, and to be willing to come into this Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Liberty, and take their ſhare in it peaceably, and do not give any juſt Provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; For <hi>the Wrath of a King is as the Roaring of a Lyon; and where the Word of a King is, there is Power:</hi> And ceaſe to caſt dirt upon the new Regulation, for it is of God, and it will ſtand, maugre all the Powers of Hell that ſhall oppoſe it: And the old way and path of Government, that hath its Ground and Foundation, and is Built upon Mens Souls and Conſciences, is of the Devil, and muſt all paſs away and fall.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:50785:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>O that we might all be Wiſe, and Unite, and Love as Brethren and <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Men; what though we be not all of one Opinion? The World never was ſo happy yet: But let us all be of one Mind, and of one Heart as to this, <hi>viz. To love and like this Chriſtian Liberty, and contribute our Aſſistance thereunto;</hi> which is our Duty to His Majeſty in the Confirmation thereof: And I do not doubt, but that when once the Nation hath taſted this New Wine of Peace and Tranquility, which the Eſtabliſhment of this Liberty will bring along with it, but a little while; they will not deſire to drink of the Old, they will never thirſt more to be in the Old Captive State and Condition again, of <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts;</hi> and it will ſoon be a means, to make us the moſt Potent Nation in <hi>Chriſtendom:</hi> Therefore, let us all joyn Heart and Hand with His Gracious Majeſty in this good work, of ſetting up the <hi>New Heavens,</hi> and the <hi>New Earth, wherein ſhall dwell Righteouſneſs;</hi> and not to conſult with <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood.</hi> But let us truſt in the Lord, and be of good Courage; let no man's Heart fail him, but let us all fix our Hands to the Plow, and not look back; for he that does, makes himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and unworthy of ſo great a Mercy as Chriſtian Liberty. O dear Hearts! Shut the Doors round about ye, ſecure your Chriſtian Liberty as firm as you can; make Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Walls unto it; I am not againſt that; but my great aim, with reſpect to you, is to cure you of your ſlaviſh Fears and Jealouſies: But you will ſay, <hi>Why do you mix and complicate Religious and Civil Things together?</hi> Why, my Anſwer is, <hi>Becauſe it is a mix'd Complicated Diſeaſe; it is a Diſtemper that is made up of Religious and Civil Compounds:</hi> And therefore the Remedy, muſt be a mix'd Complicated Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; it muſt be proper and ſuitable to the Diſeaſe; for the Diſeaſe is an old intermix'd Diſeaſe, and therefore the Doſe muſt be ſuitable thereunto. Thus I have done with you my Dear Countrey-men all, and I ſhall conclude like a Poor Scholar, with a piece of the Liturgy, <hi>viz. From the Tyranny and Oppreſſion of all inhumane Penal Laws, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly Teſts, Libera nos Domine;</hi> And let every honeſt <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Man ſay, <hi>Amen</hi> to it.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere are ſome literal faults Eſcaped the Preſs, which thou art deſired to correct; but the moſt material, is in <hi>Page</hi> 21. <hi>line</hi> 9. where for <hi>Nineteen Articles,</hi> read <hi>Nineteenth Article.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THere is lately Publiſhed by the ſame Author, A Book, Entituled, <hi>A New TEST in lieu of the Old One;</hi> By way of Suppoſition; Or, A Satisfactory Anſwer to that Great and Common Question, viz. <hi>If the Penal Laws and Teſts ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed, how ſhall the Proteſtant Religion and Intereſt be ſecured?</hi> The Second Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with Conſiderable Additions; and an Anſwer to ſeveral Objections. Printed and Sold by <hi>George Larkin,</hi> at the <hi>Two Swans</hi> without <hi>Biſhopſgate.</hi> Price 6d.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
